<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Three small and plaine treatises 1. Of prayer or actiue 2. Of principles, or positiue 3. Resolutions, or oppositiue Diuinitie. Translated and collected out of the auncient writers for the priuate vse of a most noble ladie. By an old praebendary of the Church of Lincolne.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1620</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 119 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 83 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13949</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24259</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102025</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837826</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837826</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2171</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13949)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2171)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1040:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Three small and plaine treatises 1. Of prayer or actiue 2. Of principles, or positiue 3. Resolutions, or oppositiue Diuinitie. Translated and collected out of the auncient writers for the priuate vse of a most noble ladie. By an old praebendary of the Church of Lincolne.</title>
                  <author>Williams, John, 1582-1650.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 163, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By J. Bill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1620]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>On title page, the word "Diuinitie" is preceded by a brace bracket.</note>
                  <note>"Old praebendary" = Abp. John Williams.</note>
                  <note>"For the priuate use of the L.M.B.".--NUC Pre-1956?.</note>
                  <note>Print faded and show-through; pages marked and stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2171:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2171:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THREE SMALL AND plaine <hi>Treatiſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Of Prayers or <hi>Actiue</hi> Diuinitie.</item>
               <item>2. Of Principles, or <hi>Poſitiue</hi> Diuinitie.</item>
               <item>3. Reſolutions, or <hi>Oppoſitiue</hi> Diuinitie.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Tranſlated and collected out of the Auncient Writers for the priuate vſe of a moſt Noble <hi>Ladie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By an old <hi>PRAEBENDARY</hi> of the Church of <hi>Lincolne.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:2171:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2171:2"/>
            <head>CERTAINE PRAYERS, AND ſhort MEDITATIONS tranſlated out of the Writings of S. Auguſtine, S. Gregorie, <hi>S.</hi> Bernard, Ioannes Picus Miran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dula, Ludouicus Viues, Georgius Caſſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, Charolus Paſchalius, and others, for the priuate Vſe of the L. M. B.</head>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>Morning Prayer.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y Soule fleeth vnto the Lord before the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Watch,<note place="margin">Pſal. 130.6.</note> I ſay, before the morning Watch.</p>
               <p>O let me heare thy louing kindneſſe betimes in the morning,<note place="margin">Pſal. 143.8.</note> for in thee is my truſt: ſhew thou mee the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:2171:3"/> way, that I ſhould walke in, for I lift vp my ſoule vnto thee.</p>
               <p>O Lord aſſiſt mee with thy holy Spirit in my pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, And let my cry come vnto thee.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Our Father which art, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>A Prayer for Confeſsion of ſins.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">S. Greg. Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mil. <hi>33.</hi> in Iob.</note>REceiue (O Lord) in the armes of thy mercie, thy diſtreſſed hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maiden, who in <hi>remorſe</hi> and <hi>contrition,</hi> returnes vnto thee from her ſinnes. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the life of that ſinner is not abhorred of thee,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:2171:3"/> which is accompanied with ſighes, and repentance. Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don then (O Lord) all my offences for thy deare Sons ſake. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>A Prayer for the Morning.</head>
                  <p>ALmighty God,<note place="margin">Georg. Caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſander Pres. Eccleſ.</note> our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Father, which haſt brought me thy hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maiden to this preſent mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, protect mee ſtill with thy mighty power, that this enſuing day, I may fall into no ſinne, nor run into any kinde of danger, but that my thoughts, wordes, and deedes may tend to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:2171:4"/> and glory of thy name, and the eternall comfort, and ſaluation of mine own ſoule, through Ieſus Chriſt my Lord, and onely Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Viues.</note>O Moſt ſyncere, and pure <hi>Light,</hi> from whence this light of the day, and of the <hi>Sunne</hi> fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth his beginning; Thou which <hi>enlighteneſt</hi> euery man, that commeth into the world. Thou <hi>Light,</hi> whome no night, or eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning can obſcure, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinueſt euer in thy High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noone <hi>brightneſſe.</hi> Thou
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:2171:4"/> 
                     <hi>Word,</hi> and <hi>Wiſedome</hi> of ſo great a Father, enlighten this morning my ſoule, and vnderſtanding, that thy weake handmaiden may be this day as blinded to the <hi>Vanities</hi> of the world; and quick-ſighted only to thoſe things, which are pleaſing vnto thee, and leading to the wayes of thy Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>For the Mediation of Chriſt.</head>
                  <p>LOrd Ieſus,<note place="margin">Greg. Hom. <hi>7.</hi> in Ezech.</note> that art not onely righteous, but <hi>righteouſneſſe</hi> it ſelfe, and art my <hi>Aduocate</hi> with
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:2171:5"/> God the Father, iuſtifie thou me thy hand-maiden in the day of iudgement, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I acknowledge, and accuſe my ſelf, as full of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtice, and pollution. For it is not vpon any action, or contrition of mine owne, that my ſoule relies, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vpon a faith, aſſurance, and bolde confidence in thee, mine <hi>Aduocate,</hi> who liueſt, and raigneſt with the Father, and the holy Ghoſt, one God, world without end. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:2171:5"/>
                  <head>Againſt Temptations.</head>
                  <p>GIue me thy grace (O Almighty God) ſo to vanquiſh,<note place="margin">Aug. Serm. <hi>86.</hi> de ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis Domini.</note> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome the <hi>lusts,</hi> and <hi>temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations</hi> of this world, that I may triumph with thee o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the <hi>Diuell,</hi> and his wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked <hi>angels</hi> in the world to come. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>For Piety.</head>
                  <p>I Humbly beſeech thee (O Almighty God) that this deſire of <hi>reading,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Aug. Serm. <hi>82.</hi>
                     </note> and <hi>hearing</hi> thy ſacred <hi>Word,</hi>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:2171:6"/> which by thy holy Spirit thou haſt planted in my heart, may by thy grace, and mercie be daily <hi>renued,</hi> and <hi>augmented</hi> vnto a perfect fire of zeale, and deuotion to the honor of thy Name, and ſaluation of mine owne ſoule in Chriſt Ieſu. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>A Prayer for a Noble-woman.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Carolus Paſchalius.</note>O Lord Ieſus Chriſt, that art ſo far from contemning <hi>Nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie</hi> of birth, that thy Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſts haue diligently ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched out, and recorded thine owne <hi>genealogie,</hi> giue
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:2171:6"/> me thy vnworthy hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayden the grace, that I a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe not by <hi>ingratitude</hi> this thy fauour, and mercie. But rather, as it was firſt acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in my Aunceſtors, let it ſtill be preſerued in my per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, by my continuall ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of thee, and doing (as it ſhall lie in my power) all workes of Charity to my neighbours. Giue me grace, that as thou haſt plac't mee in <hi>Birth,</hi> and <hi>rancke,</hi> ſo I may be found in <hi>deuotion, pietie, lowlineſſe of minde, meekneſſe,</hi> and a religious care of thy <hi>worſhip,</hi> conſpicuous a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue others. And if it bee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hy gracious will to make
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:2171:7"/> me a mother of children, and a miſtreſſe of a family, let me appeare a <hi>patterne</hi> and <hi>enſample</hi> of deuotion, and pietie to all that are about mee. And make mee and them ſo to liue in thy <hi>feare,</hi> that we may die in thy <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour,</hi> through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord, and onely Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>A Prayer for a Wife.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Charolus Paſchal.</note>ALmighty God, which haſte giuen me to be a <hi>comforter,</hi> and an <hi>hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per</hi> vnto my husband, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due my ſoule with thoſe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:2171:7"/> heauenly Graces, wherwith I may be moſt enabled to ſerue thee, and pleaſe him. Knit our mindes, as well as our bodies in an indiſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble band of ſyncere affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Giue either of vs ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified hearts, zealous to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards thee, thankefull to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards our Soueraigne, ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, and louing one to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards another. Crowne withal, if it be thy will, theſe chaſte <hi>intentions</hi> with thy fructifying <hi>Grace,</hi> that wee may become the happy Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents of ſuch <hi>Oliue branches,</hi> as may one day aduance thy glory in this Church, and Commonwealth. In a
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:2171:8"/> word, ſo incorporate vs both by faith in Chriſt vnto thy kingdom of Grace, that we may at the laſt attaine vnto thy kingdome of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>A prayer for one attendant neere the perſon of a Prince.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Carolus Paſchal.</note>ALmighty God, by whoſe gracious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence it commeth, that my <hi>Lord,</hi> and <hi>Husband</hi> is thus employed in that neerneſſe of attendance vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his <hi>Royall Maieſtie,</hi> giue him grace ſo to <hi>ſerue thee, that hee may the better ſerue
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:2171:8"/> him,</hi> and by making him thy <hi>Saint,</hi> continue him his <hi>ſeruant.</hi> Fill his mind with all wiſedome, knowledge, and other vertues befitting his ranck and calling, that he may ſeeme no more <hi>ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted</hi> by the King, then <hi>ſele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted</hi> by thee for theſe em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments. Make him vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilant, carefull, and indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious in his Maſters af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aires. Make him to accompt it his onely <hi>happineſſe</hi> to ſerue thee, his onely <hi>vertue</hi> to obſerue him, and all the reſt as glittering <hi>vanity.</hi> That after a troubleſome, but long life in a <hi>Kings</hi> Court, his ſoule may bee
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:2171:9"/> carried by the Angels vnto <hi>thy</hi> Court, where <hi>one day is better then a thouſand.</hi> Grant this for thy deare Sonnes ſake Ieſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <head>Meditation. <hi>Count MIRANDVLA,</hi> his twelue Thoughts, or weapons againſt all the <hi>temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> of Sinne.</head>
                  <list>
                     <head>Thinke</head>
                     <item n="1">
                        <note place="margin">Io. Pici Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randulae Doctr. Salu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tif.</note>1 THe pleaſure thou art tempted vnto, but <hi>ſhort,</hi> and <hi>momentarie.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item n="2">2 And euen this is atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:2171:9"/> with <hi>loathing</hi> and <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xietie.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item n="3">3 And yet that for this, thou muſt looſe <hi>Heauen.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item n="4">4 That thy <hi>life</hi> is but as a <hi>dreame</hi> and <hi>ſhadow.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item n="5">5 Thy <hi>death</hi> is <hi>ſuddaine,</hi> and at thy doore.</item>
                     <item n="6">6 Thy time of <hi>repentance caſuall,</hi> and <hi>vncertaine.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item n="7">7 Thy <hi>reward,</hi> or <hi>puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> endleſſe and <hi>eternall.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item n="8">8 That <hi>thou</hi> art a creature of an <hi>excellent worth,</hi> and made to ſerue <hi>God.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item n="9">9 That thou haſt no hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe to the <hi>peace of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item n="10">10 Thinke how <hi>good thy God</hi> hath bin vnto thee.</item>
                     <item n="11">
                        <pb n="16" facs="tcp:2171:10"/>11 Thinke of the <hi>Croſſe,</hi> and of <hi>Christ,</hi> who there <hi>died for thee.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item n="12">12 Of <hi>examples</hi> of <hi>holy men</hi> and <hi>Saints,</hi> who liued be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Walke about your chamber a turne or two after your prayers, and meditate vpon theſe points ſeriouſly, and you ſhall finde, that temptations to ſinne will va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh away, and leaue to aſſault you.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The <hi>4. laſt</hi> things to bee <hi>firſt thought vpon</hi> by all good Chriſtians.</head>
                  <list>
                     <item n="1">
                        <note place="margin">Bern. Bona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent. Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſ. Carthuſ.</note>1 The day of thy <hi>death,</hi> thou knoweſt not how ſuddenly.</item>
                     <item n="2">2 The day of <hi>iudgement,</hi> that will come certainely.</item>
                     <item n="3">3 The ioyes of <hi>heauen,</hi> if thou liue religiouſly.</item>
                     <item n="4">4 The paines of <hi>hell,</hi> if thou con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinueſt to doe wickedly.</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <trailer>The end of Morning prayer.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:2171:10"/>
               <head>Euening Prayer to bed-ward.</head>
               <p>O Lord heare my prayer.</p>
               <p>And let my cry come vnto thee.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Our Father which art, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>A Prayer for Euening.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> LORD,<note place="margin">Carol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> Paſchal.</note> I doe confeſſe to my ſhame, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, that this <hi>day</hi> hath beene ſpent by me with leſſe puritie, and pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, then it ſhould haue bin. I haue augmented ſithence this <hi>morning</hi> the ſcore of my ſinnes. My <hi>thoughts</hi> haue beene <hi>polluted,</hi> my <hi>wit</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:2171:11"/> and <hi>vnſanctified,</hi> my <hi>tongue</hi> more <hi>raſh,</hi> and <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridled,</hi> then became any one of that rancke, and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, wherein thou haſt ſet me. I haue ſinned through <hi>idleneſſe, ignorance, ſlouthful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> and <hi>malice.</hi> And this <hi>darkneſſe</hi> of the night puts mee in minde of that eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall <hi>darkneſſe</hi> my ſinnes haue deſerued. Pardon, and forgiue me all my tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions. Let this darkeneſſe bee a fit time vnto mee of <hi>reſt,</hi> and <hi>ſleepe,</hi> and no op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie of <hi>ſnares,</hi> and <hi>temptations.</hi> Send thy holy Ghoſt into my heart, to free, and purifie the ſame from
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:2171:11"/> all <hi>rolling motions,</hi> and ſugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions of Sathan, and from the vſuall <hi>terrours,</hi> and <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frightments</hi> of the night. Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue this houſe in ſafety (O Lord) and all the people that are therein. <hi>Let my prayer aſcend vp vnto thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence as the incenſe, and let this lifting vp of mine hands be as an Euening ſacrifice,</hi> through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord, and onely Sauiour. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>HAuing ſpent the <hi>day,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Viues.</note> wee betake our<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſelues to our repoſe in the <hi>night.</hi> So after the troubles of this preſent <hi>life,</hi>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:2171:12"/> wee ſhall reſt our ſelues in <hi>death.</hi> Nothing doth more reſemble our <hi>life</hi> then the <hi>day,</hi> our <hi>death</hi> then <hi>ſleepe,</hi> our <hi>graue</hi> then the <hi>bed,</hi> and our <hi>reſurrection</hi> then our <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waking</hi> in the morning. Doe thou then, O God my pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectour, and defender, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue me in my <hi>ſleepe,</hi> from the incurſions, and tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the <hi>diuell,</hi> and in my <hi>death</hi> from the guilt and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments of my <hi>ſinnes.</hi> I haue no <hi>ſtrength</hi> to reſiſt in the one, nor <hi>merits</hi> of mine owne to diſplay in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Looke only vpon the merits of my <hi>Lord,</hi> and <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour,</hi> and giue mee a ſtrong,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:2171:12"/> and ſtedfaſt <hi>faith,</hi> to <hi>apply</hi> his righteouſneſſe to mine owne ſoule. In confidence, and full aſſurance of whoſe <hi>ſatisfactions</hi> for all my ſins, I doe for this <hi>night lie mee downe in peace, and take my reſt, for it is that Lord onely, that maketh mee to continue in ſafetie. Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>ALmighty,<note place="margin">G. Caſſ.</note> and euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting God, who makeſt the <hi>light</hi> to ſucceed the <hi>dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> giue mee the grace to ſpend this <hi>night</hi> freed from the <hi>ſnares</hi> of <hi>ſinne</hi> and <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than,</hi> and to bee here againe vpon my knees in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:2171:13"/> to giue thee thankes for the ſame, through Ieſus Chriſt my Lord, and onely Sauiour. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="meditations">
               <head>MEDITATIONS. When your mayd is getting you to bed.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iues.</note>HEe that willingly goes to <hi>bed,</hi> ſhould as willingly goe to his <hi>graue.</hi> We willingly put off our <hi>cloathes,</hi> being to put them on againe in the <hi>mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning:</hi> and ſhould as willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly put off our <hi>bodies,</hi> beeing to put them on againe in the <hi>Reſurrection.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:2171:13"/>2 After the troubles of the <hi>day</hi> comes the quietnes of the <hi>night,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Viues.</note> in the which the King, and the ſwaine differ nothing: ſo after this <hi>life</hi> comes <hi>death;</hi> where poore, and rich are alike, and equall.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Here is a fit time (eſpecially layd in your bed) to fall to your <hi>Audite</hi> for the day paſt.<note place="margin">The practiſe of the Kings Maieſty, as I haue heard</note>
               </p>
               <p>What euill you haue commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by
<list>
                     <item>1. <hi>Swearing.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. <hi>Lying.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. <hi>Taunting.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>4. <hi>Beeing too angry.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>5. <hi>Vaine tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, eſpecially of Religion.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>6. <hi>Exceeding in fare or appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>7. <hi>Iniuring of another.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list> Repent of it. Deteſt it. Reſolue to doe it no more.</p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:2171:14"/>
               <p>What good you haue <hi>omitted,</hi> as
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Saying grace when you eate.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Praying.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Releeuing of a poore bodie.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting your</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>husband</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>parents.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Spending ſome time vpon Meditations.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Works of charitie.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list> Deſire Gods grace to be more warie.</p>
               <p>What <hi>good</hi> you haue performed
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>If you haue</hi> learned <hi>any thing that day.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>If you haue done any man</hi> good <hi>that day.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>If you haue kept your</hi> priuate and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like prayers, <hi>that day.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>If you haue giuen any</hi> almes <hi>that day.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>If you haue heard the</hi> Word, <hi>or recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the</hi> Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>that day.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>If you haue ſpent any time vpon your</hi> Meditatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s <hi>that day.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list> 
                  <hi>Reioyce</hi> in it, and giue <hi>God</hi> thankes for it.</p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:2171:14"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>When you haue runne ouer theſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compts, and finde ſleepe comming, ſay,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Into thy hands I commit my Spirit, for thou haſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed me (O Lord) thou God of truth. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>The end of Euening prayer.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayers">
               <head>Some other Collects.</head>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>
                     <hi>For</hi> Faith.</head>
                  <p>MAn is <hi>blinded</hi> by ſin,<note place="margin">
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iues.</note> but thou (O Chriſt) by the goodnes and mercie of God the Father, art become our <hi>guide</hi> in the way of ſaluation. And yet ſuch is our wretchedneſſe,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:2171:15"/> and miſerie, that we <hi>ſtagger</hi> for all this, ſometimes not vnderſtanding, ſometimes not beleeuing, many times not applying to our ſoules with a ſure confidence thy promiſes of <hi>ſaluation</hi> ſet downe in the <hi>Goſpell.</hi> O mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerably <hi>blind</hi> that we are, that can neither <hi>ſee</hi> our ſelues, nor <hi>beleeue</hi> our gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and inſtructer. O thou eternall, and pure <hi>veritie,</hi> vouchſafe ſo to ſlide into our hearts, that we may be more certainely perſwaded of thee, and thy <hi>Truth,</hi> then of thoſe things wee <hi>ſee</hi> with our <hi>eyes, heare</hi> with our <hi>eares,</hi> and <hi>handle</hi> with our <hi>handes,</hi>
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:2171:15"/> the weake apprehenſions of our bodily ſenſes, vpon which this <hi>fleſh</hi> and <hi>blood</hi> doeth ſo much depend. Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſe and aſſwage thoſe <hi>rol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling thoughts,</hi> and wandring <hi>motions</hi> of the fleſh, that make vs to <hi>doubt,</hi> and ſtag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in thoſe high <hi>myſteries,</hi> of the which wee ought moſt firmely to bee fixed, and <hi>reſolued. Faith</hi> is thy gift, and therefore worke it by the <hi>holy Ghoſt</hi> in my heart, that all my ſenſes, and ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations may become ſlaues, and captiues to the ſame. <hi>Lord, I beleeue, helpe thou mine vnbeleefe. O Lord increaſe my faith.</hi> Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:2171:16"/>
                  <head>MEDITATION.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <note place="margin">
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iues.</note>1 How eaſily wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue a lewd, and lying <hi>man,</hi> and yet how ſcrupulous we are to beleeue <hi>God</hi> himſelfe.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 We beleeue a <hi>man</hi> in things, which <hi>nothing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne</hi> vs; we beleeue not <hi>God</hi> in matters of our <hi>ſaluation.</hi> Man is <hi>impotent,</hi> God <hi>omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3 We beleeue our <hi>ſenſes,</hi> which often delude vs, as in all trickes of <hi>Legeyr-demaine:</hi> we diſtruſt <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who can neither be <hi>deceiued,</hi> nor <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue</hi> vs.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:2171:16"/>
                  <head>For the King, and the Royall Iſſue.</head>
                  <p>I Humbly beſeech thee,<note place="margin">G. Caſſ.</note> Almighty God, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent with all bleſſings of goodneſſe, our King, and his Royall iſſue. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe vpon them day by day all thy fauours, van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſh with thy mighty hand, all open enemies, and priuie <hi>Conſpirators,</hi> who op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugne their <hi>religion, life, dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deme,</hi> or <hi>dignitie.</hi> Crowne each of them with all ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, theſe vertues with long liues, and their liues at the laſt with eternall glory. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:2171:17"/>
                  <head>For Charitie, or the workes of Mercie.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Auguſt. Meditat.</note>O Lord of mercie, and compaſſion, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee by the tender bowels of thy Sonne Chriſt Ieſus, to mooue my ſtonie <hi>heart</hi> to the <hi>workes of mercie,</hi> that I may keepe my <hi>howers</hi> of prayers, <hi>mourne</hi> with them that mourne, <hi>counſell</hi> them that are amiſſe, <hi>helpe</hi> them that are in miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, <hi>releeue</hi> the poore, <hi>comfort</hi> the ſorrowfull, <hi>helpe</hi> the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, <hi>forgiue</hi> them that treſpaſſe againſt me, <hi>pray</hi> for them that hate mee, <hi>requite</hi>
                     <pb n="31" facs="tcp:2171:17"/> good for euil, <hi>deſpiſe</hi> no man or woman, <hi>reuerence</hi> my betters, <hi>reſpect</hi> my equals, be <hi>humble,</hi> and courteous to my inferiors: <hi>imitate</hi> thoſe that are good: <hi>ſhunne</hi> thoſe that are bad: <hi>embrace</hi> ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, <hi>eſchew</hi> vice. Be <hi>patient</hi> in aduerſitie, <hi>modeſt</hi> in proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peritie, <hi>thankfull</hi> in either. Keepe a watch ouer my <hi>tongue. Scorne</hi> this world, and <hi>thirſt</hi> after heauen. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>For the receiuing of the B. Sacrament.</head>
                  <p>O Lord Ieſus Chriſt the onely begotten Sonne of God,<note place="margin">G. Caſſ.</note> tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough whom onely is gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:2171:18"/> forgiueneſſe of ſinnes, and life euerlaſting, who diddeſt iuſtifie the <hi>Publican,</hi> when he confeſſed, the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of <hi>Chanaan,</hi> when ſhee prayed, <hi>Peter</hi> when hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented, and the <hi>thiefe vpon the Croſſe,</hi> when hee called vpon thee, grant vnto me, a moſt miſerable, and wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched ſinner, pardon and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueneſſe of all my tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions, which I moſt humbly confeſſe I haue committed againſt thee: that I may receiue this <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of thy body and blood,</hi> not to my iudgement, and condemnation, but to my euerlaſting comfort and ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:2171:18"/> who liueſt and raig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt with the Father, and the holy Ghoſt, one God world without end. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>Meditation When you haue newly receiued.</head>
                  <p>O Lord encreaſe my faith, O Lord,<note place="margin">G. Caſſ.</note> let the <hi>body and blood</hi> of Chriſt be fixed in my ſoule to my comfort in this life, and eternall ſaluation in the life to come. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:2171:19"/>
                  <head>For that day you expect to heare a Sermon, or when you reade vpon your Bible.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">G. Caſſ.</note>ALlmighty, and euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting God, whoſe <hi>Word is a lanterne to our feete, and a light vnto our pathes,</hi> open and enlighten my vnderſtanding, that I may learne the myſteries of thy <hi>Word,</hi> ſo farre foorth, as is neceſſary to my ſaluation, purely and ſyncerely: and bee ſo transfigured in my life and conuerſation, vnto that which I ſhall learne, as to pleaſe thee in will, and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:2171:19"/> deede, through Ieſus Chriſt my Lord, and onely Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For ſickneſſe, and all other vſes, you haue excellent Prayers in the Booke of Common prayers.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="treatise">
            <head>
               <hi>PRINCIPLES.</hi> Few Notes for the priuate vſe of my L. M. B.</head>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer to be ſaid vpon your knees, before the reading o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer of theſe Notes.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lmightie God, the Fountaine of true Wiſedome and knowledge, ſend thy holy Spirit into
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:2171:20"/> my heart, that I may <hi>ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently</hi> vnderſtand, and <hi>ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fastly</hi> beleeue all the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines <hi>neceſſary</hi> to my Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, and adde ſuch <hi>pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe</hi> and <hi>obedience</hi> to this Faith, thorough the whole courſe of my life and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation, as I may ſo ſerue thee in thy kingdome of Grace, that hereafter I may be made partaker of thy kingdom of Glory, through the onely merit and media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thy deare Sonne, and my deare Sauiour <hi>Ieſus Christ. Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="principle">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:2171:20"/>
               <head>I.</head>
               <p>MAn, ſithence his fall in <hi>Adam,</hi> hath no hope of ſaluation, but by the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant of Grace</hi> betwixt <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Man;</hi> Whereby <hi>God</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth vnto man, Mercie and Forgiueneſſe of Sinnes, and man vnto God, true Faith <hi>in Chriſt</hi> and holines of life and conuerſation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="principle">
               <head>II.</head>
               <p>ALl men haue not inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt in this Couenant of Grace, but they onely that are of Gods Church: Now the Church of God is;</p>
               <p>Any Company or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of men whereſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:2171:21"/> liuing, called by God through the ſound of the Goſpel, vnto the Faith of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and diſtinguiſhed from other Societies by theſe fiue Marks eſpecially, 1. hearing and reading the <hi>Word,</hi> 2. <hi>Faith</hi> thereunto, 3. the vſe of the <hi>Sacraments,</hi> 4. <hi>Prayer,</hi> and 5. <hi>Sanctity</hi> of life.</p>
               <p>Where theſe fiue things are, there is euer a Church of God and ſufficient means of ſaluation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="principle">
               <head>III.</head>
               <p>THe Word muſt be read often vpon your Bible, with modeſty and ſhort de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires of the heart vnto God,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:2171:21"/> to giue you grace to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it, to beleeue it, and to practiſe it, It muſt bee heard vpon all conuenient occaſions, eſpecially in thoſe two houres of the Sabbath day, appointed by the Church and the State for that Diuine worſhip, and then you muſt obſerue foure Rules.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Obſerue the Preacher with attention &amp; modeſtie.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Secondly, apply vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your ſelfe in particular, the Doctrines and Vſes which are deliuered in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Examine your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience if you be guilty of
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:2171:22"/> the ſinnes there reproued, and preſently call to God for grace to amend them.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Thinke vpon theſe things againe when you come to your Chamber.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="principle">
               <head>IIII.</head>
               <p>THis outward hearing and reading of the Word, together with the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward working of the holy Ghoſt in your heart, doeth beget a true, liuely and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing faith, which is,</p>
               <p>A certaine knowledge and aſſurance of the heart that all is true which God hath ſpoken or promiſed in the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:2171:22"/> Scripture, and that you reſt wholly and confidently vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on God, that he hath gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto your ſelfe in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, forgiuenes of ſinnes, and true righteouſneſſe in <hi>Chriſt Ieſus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is the maine point you are ſeriouſly to medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate vpon, and therefore ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue theſe precepts,</p>
               <p n="1">1. If you doe not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, or if you doe doubt of any thing in Scripture, preſently pray vnto God to ſtrengthen and enlighten you.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If you doubt whether
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:2171:23"/> you may haue any particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar intereſt in thoſe generall promiſes of grace in <hi>Christ,</hi> propounded in the Goſpel, fall againe to your prayers for an increaſe of <hi>Faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. If you doubt, and yet can finde in your heart to pray for more faith, Let your conſcience neuer bee troubled with ſuch a <hi>doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Marke well when the Creed is in reading, and giue an aſſent with your heart to euery Article. And (as I doubt not you haue learned it) ſo keepe it ſtill in memorie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="principle">
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:2171:23"/>
               <head>V.</head>
               <p>NOw as this faith of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſinnes, and righteouſneſſe in <hi>Chriſt</hi> is wrought in vs by the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and hearing of the Word ioyned with Prayer, ſo is it <hi>ſigned</hi> and <hi>ſealed</hi> in our hearts by the two Bleſſed <hi>Sacraments.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="sacraments">
                  <head>Baptiſme. The Lords Supper.</head>
                  <p>Obſerue in either Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament two parts.
<list>
                        <item>A viſible ſigne
<list>
                              <item>Water in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme.</item>
                              <item>Bread &amp; Wine in the Supper.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>An inuiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble grace.
<list>
                              <item>Remiſsion of ſinnes in Baptiſme.</item>
                              <item>The benefite of Chriſts paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="principle">
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:2171:24"/>
               <head>VI.</head>
               <p>BAptiſme is the firſt Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the new Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, to wit,</p>
               <p>An outward waſhing of Water appointed by Chriſt in his Church, with this promiſe, that vpon your being Baptized, you were as certainely waſhed from your ſinnes Original being an infant, and actuall, if you had beene of yeeres, by the holy Ghoſt, and the Blood of Chriſt, as you were rin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed outwardly in body by this Element of Water.</p>
               <div type="uses">
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:2171:24"/>
                  <head>Marke then theſe vſes of <hi>Baptiſme.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p n="1">1. It aſſures vs wee are wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed from our ſinnes by the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> and the Blood of <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. It keeps vs from deſpaire, becauſe it aſſures vs our ſinnes are waſhed away.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. It keepes vs from ſinne: for it is a ſhame for one waſhed to ſoile himſelfe againe.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. It giues an entrance into the Church.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. It hath a
<list>
                        <item>viſible ſigne.
<list>
                              <item>Water.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>Grace inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible.
<list>
                              <item>Forgiueneſſe of ſinnes by the blood of Chriſt.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="principle">
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:2171:25"/>
               <head>VII.</head>
               <p>THe Lords Supper is a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribution of Bread and Wine, which ſeales, ſignes and exhibits, or giues vnto you <hi>Chriſts</hi> true Body offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and his true Blood pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out vpon the Croſſe, for your ſinnes, as certainely, as the Prieſts exhibite vnto your hands the Bread and the Wine. And withall, the Supper aſſures your heart, that <hi>Chriſts</hi> Body and Blood nouriſh your ſoule to perpetual life, as ſurely, as Bread and Wine doth nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh your body to the offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of this temporall life.</p>
               <div type="uses">
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:2171:25"/>
                  <head>Marke then the vſes of this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the Supper.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. It aſſures you of all the benefit that is to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected from the Bodie and blood of <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. It puts you continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in minde that <hi>Chriſt</hi> dyed for you.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. It ſtrengthens and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaines your faith, if it be receiued worthily. And therefore you muſt not neglect (twice in the yeere at the leaſt) to approch with all reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence this heauenly Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="principle">
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:2171:26"/>
               <head>VIII.</head>
               <p>THat this Sacrament may be receiued wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily, you muſt <hi>examin</hi> your ſelfe before the receiuing, <hi>Pray</hi> vnto God for <hi>Faith</hi> in the receiuing, and take heed of <hi>groſſe</hi> and <hi>premeditated</hi> ſinnes after the receiuing of this <hi>Sacrament.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="principle">
               <head>IX.</head>
               <p>BEfore the receiuing, you muſt examine foure things:</p>
               <p n="1">1. You muſt examin your knowledge,
<list>
                     <item>1. <hi>Whether you know how you ought to liue. To this end read ouer the</hi> 10. Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</item>
                     <item>2. <hi>Whether you know how to</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue. <hi>Read ouer attentiuely your</hi> Creed.</item>
                     <item>3. <hi>Whether you know how to</hi> Pray. <hi>Say ouer aduiſedly the</hi> Lords Prayer.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:2171:26"/>
               <p>Without this little know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge (at the leaſt) you are not fit to Receiue.</p>
               <p n="2">2. You muſt examine your <hi>faith</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Whether you are aſſured in your heart, that</hi> Chriſt <hi>hath fully ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied for your ſins, and perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reconciled you vnto God, not others only, but your ſelfe alſo.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Without this <hi>aſſurance</hi> (in ſome meaſure) you may not receiue.</p>
               <p n="3">3. You muſt examine your <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. <hi>Whether you are</hi> ſory <hi>for your ſinnes.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. <hi>Whether you</hi> hate <hi>ſinne.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. <hi>Whether you</hi> reſolue <hi>to indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to</hi> ſinne no more.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Without this <hi>Repentance</hi> you cannot receiue wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily.</p>
               <p n="4">4. You muſt examine your <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>1.<hi>Whether you forgiue all the world.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. <hi>Whether you are free from malice and hatred.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>When you haue exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned theſe foure points you may receiue worthily.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="principle">
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:2171:27"/>
               <head>X.</head>
               <p>NOw your faith in <hi>Chriſt</hi> which you haue gotten in Gods Church, being thus <hi>hatched</hi> by the holy Ghoſt in your heart, brought foorth by your <hi>hearing,</hi> che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed by your <hi>reading</hi> of the <hi>word,</hi> ſealed by your <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> and ſtrongly confirmed and ſtrengthened by your partaking of the bleſſed <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament</hi> of the <hi>Supper,</hi> muſt be continually maintained and preſerued by theſe two meanes,</p>
               <p>Prayer <hi>vnto God &amp; him only.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And</p>
               <p>Good works, <hi>or holines of life.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="summary">
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:2171:27"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>And this is the ſumme of all your notes which I recommend vnto you for this time.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Saluation</hi> is only by faith in <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Faith</hi> onely in Gods Church.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Where,</hi> by the <hi>Word</hi> read or heard, Faith is nouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed.</p>
               <p n="4">4. By the Sacrament of <hi>Baptiſme</hi> aſſured.</p>
               <p n="5">5. By the Sacrament of the <hi>Supper</hi> ratified and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed.</p>
               <p n="6">6. By <hi>Prayer</hi> and <hi>Good workes</hi> for euer eſtabliſhed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:2171:28"/>
               <head>A Prayer after the reading of theſe few Notes.</head>
               <p>O <hi>Lord God,</hi> that I may be partaker of thy <hi>couenant</hi> of <hi>Grace,</hi> make me a beleeuing mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of thy Church, ſend thy holy Spirit into my heart to beget there a <hi>confidence</hi> and full <hi>aſſurance</hi> of the remiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all my ſinnes in <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> let this aſſurance bee ſtill <hi>nouriſhed</hi> with my <hi>hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi> and <hi>reading</hi> of the <hi>Word,</hi> let it be ſealed vnto mee by my <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> confirmed by the Sacrament of the <hi>Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,</hi> and fully eſtabliſhed by
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:2171:28"/> my ſeruing of thee in <hi>Prayer</hi> and <hi>Good workes,</hi> to the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of thy Name, and the endleſſe comfort and ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of mine owne ſoule, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="catechism">
            <pb facs="tcp:2171:29"/>
            <head>¶ A SHORT CATECHISME concerning Faith and good Workes, to be read and medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vpon once euery weeke at the leaſt: which may be well called, <hi>The Catechiſme of the Conſcience.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Queſtion.</p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hy hath GOD made me a reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Creature, and not (as well hee might) of a meaner kinde?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> That with your whole heart, that is, with your will, and vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, you might ſerue him, and loue him: which crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:2171:29"/> only indued with rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon can doe.</p>
            <p>Q. How is God princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally ſerued, and loued of mee?</p>
            <p>A. By your faith and good workes, which God commaunds you in his Word. And theſe good workes of yours are two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold,
<list>
                  <item>Prayers to God.</item>
                  <item>Charitie to men.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Q. What is Faith?</p>
            <p>A. A full beliefe, aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and perſwaſion of your heart, whereby you are vnmoueably reſolued of theſe three points:</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:2171:30"/>1. That there is one onely God, one Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, &amp; three Perſons. <hi>The</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>Father, who created you.</item>
                  <item>Sonne, who redeemed you.</item>
                  <item>Holy Ghoſt who ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified you.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That God the Sonne came into the world, to doe all that was to bee perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and to ſuffer all that was to be endured by you, for your ſinnes actuall, and originall. And hereby ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained for you perfect for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueneſſe of all your ſinnes, and hath beſtowed vpon you his owne perfect righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, by the meanes whereof you ſtand iuſt, and guiltleſſe before the throne of God.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:2171:30"/>3. That God hath prom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted with his holy Spirit the Pen-men of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, to teach you all this faith, and beleefe, as alſo all the courſe of his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. And that euery thing contained in theſe Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures is true.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Why doeth God ſo much require of mee Faith, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Becauſe without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuing in him, you cannot loue him, nor reuerence him. As if you did not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue your father to be your father, you would not loue him, or reuerence him, as your father.</p>
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:2171:31"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. How is this Faith first wrought?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. By your hearing of Gods word, and vſing thoſe two Sacraments appointed by Chriſt in his Church, Baptiſme, and the Lordes Supper: And withall, by praying continually vnto God, and doing of good workes.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How ſhall I know that I beginne to haue Faith?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. If you finde in your ſelfe theſe alterations:</p>
            <p n="1">1. If you finde, that you haue gotten more know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God, and of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, &amp; are glad therof.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If you doe deſire more
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:2171:31"/> then you did, to haue the Sonne of God to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come your Sauiour, and to ſtand betwixt you and Gods wrath for the ſinnes you haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted againſt God.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If you take more delight then you did in
<list>
                  <item>Reading and hearing the Word of God.</item>
                  <item>Receiuing the Sacrament.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. If you finde doubtings in your minde, and can pray vnto God, to ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then your Faith.</p>
            <p n="5">5. If you endeauour to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine from ſinne, for feare of offending ſo good a God.</p>
            <p n="6">6. If you beginne to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to liue godly, and
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:2171:32"/> righteouſly, becauſe it is the will, and commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God.</p>
            <p n="7">7. If you take more delight then you did in praying to God.</p>
            <p n="8">8. If you thanke God pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uately for theſe his good motions.</p>
            <p>By theſe eight points you may ſoone know, whether you haue true faith or not.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What is the infallible marke of true, and iustifying Faith?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. The effectuall apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Chriſt, and all his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits to your owne ſoule, in particular.</p>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:2171:32"/>
            <p>This appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation doeth make a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwixt iuſtifying Faith, and all other kindes of faith, which cannot ſaue vs: As
<list>
                  <item>Hiſtoricall Faith, which is a bare knowledge.</item>
                  <item>Faith of Miracles, which is a bare aſſent.</item>
                  <item>Temporary Faith, which is but a bare profeſſion of the Faith for a time, em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced onely for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of
<list>
                        <item>Knowledge.</item>
                        <item>Credite.</item>
                        <item>Profite.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What is the meaning of this aſſertion of</hi> S. Paules, <hi>that we are iuſtified by Faith alone?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. The meaning is this. Euen as when you giue your almes to a begger, it is receiued by his hand alone, and yet his hand is not alone when it receiues theſe alms, but accompanied with an arme, ſinewes, and arteries: Euen ſo, when God offers
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:2171:33"/> vnto you Chriſt, and his righteouſneſſe, you doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue him by Faith alone, and yet this Faith, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiues Chriſt is neuer alone, but ſtill accompanied with Charitie, and good workes.</p>
            <p>In a word.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To holde almes is proper to the hand, and not the arme: and to holde Chriſt, proper to Faith, and not good workes.</p>
            <p n="2">2. You are iuſtified by Faith alone, and yet if your faith be alone, it cannot iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What is the meaning of</hi> S. Iames, <hi>when hee ſayth, That wee are iuſtified by
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:2171:33"/> workes, and not by Faith?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. The meaning is this?</p>
            <p n="1">1. Faith iuſtifieth vs before God, good works before men.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Faith makes vs, good workes declare vs to bee iuſtified.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Faith giues vs our firſt iuſtificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; good works our ſecond, which is our Sanctification, or holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What is the leaſt, and weakeſt degree of Faith, that I may build vpon, to keepe mee from deſpaire, in caſe I finde not all thoſe alterations in my ſelfe, which you ſpake of before?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. 1. If you deſire Faith,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:2171:34"/> or pray vnto God, that you may deſire Faith.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If you can pray, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of God, to enable you to pray.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If you find fault with your want of faith, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire ſometimes of God to helpe this want.</p>
            <p>You are for all that the childe of God.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="treatise_in_dialogue_form">
            <pb facs="tcp:2171:34"/>
            <head>RESOLVTIONS. OPPOSITIVE <hi>DI<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>INITIE:</hi> OR The ordinary Obiections <hi>of Papiſts, against them of</hi> the <hi>reformed.</hi> Churches. DIALOGVE. <hi>Papist. Proteſtant.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Of the Church.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pap.</speaker>
                  <p>THe Church of England is no Church, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="66" facs="tcp:2171:35"/> ſtrange, conſidering your owne Writers conclude a <hi>Church</hi> to be there, where there is found <hi rend="sup">1</hi> 
                     <hi>doctrine of ſaluation,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Georg. Caſſan. conſult, titul. de <hi>Eccleſia.</hi>
                     </note> according to Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <hi rend="sup">2</hi> the <hi>vſe of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> and <hi rend="sup">3</hi> 
                     <hi>outward diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline,</hi> or Eccleſiaſticall go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement, although the <hi>Churchmen</hi> ſhould fall ſhort of thoſe Apoſtolicall, and primitiue perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, which flouriſhed in their prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſours.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pap.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea, but it is not the <hi>Catholike</hi> Church men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the <hi>Creed, I beleeue in the Catholike Church.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                  <p n="1">1. No more is the Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> for there
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:2171:35"/> was no Church at all in <hi>Rome,</hi> when the Creed was made by the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> at <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ruffin in Symb. Auguſtin. Ser. <hi>115.</hi>
                     </note> euery Apoſtle ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king his <hi>Article,</hi> when they were to depart to plant par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Churches in <hi>Rome,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Id. Serm. <hi>181.</hi> de <hi>Tempore.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>England,</hi> and other places.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. But our Church is a <hi>branch,</hi> and portion of that Catholike Church, as is alſo the<note n="a" place="margin">Theoriani collo. Damia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus à Gots. Onuphrius in vita Iulij.</note> 
                     <hi>Greeke, Armenian, Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thiopian,</hi> and <hi>Syrian</hi> as well, if not rather then the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane</hi> Church.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pap.</speaker>
                  <p>Peraduenture theſe other Churches may bee members of that <hi>Catholike</hi> Church, as ioyned and <hi>vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> with vs, but the vnion
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:2171:36"/> betwixt your Church, and ours hath beene <hi>cut aſunder</hi> aboue an hundred yeeres agone, and therefore you are quite cut off from the Catholike Church.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                  <p>This is more then you know, or then I am bound to beleeue. For</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Caſsand. conſult. pag.</hi> 930. meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpirituall conſiſting in Faith, Hope, Charitie, true Doctrine, &amp;c. <hi>Inſtitut. of a Chriſtian fol.</hi> 19.</note>This <hi>vnion</hi> of the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Catholike Church is <hi>inward,</hi> not <hi>out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,</hi> and therefore diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned onely by God himſelfe: We neuer <hi>ſundred</hi> our ſelues from the <hi>people,</hi> or <hi>Church</hi> of Rome, but from the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> or <hi>Court</hi> of Rome, not from the <hi>ſincere doctrine</hi> of that Church, but from the
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:2171:36"/> 
                     <hi>corruptions</hi> and <hi>innouations</hi> foiſted into that Church.</p>
                  <p>And therefore although we be neuer ſo hated,<note place="margin">Caſsand. ibid.</note> and excommunicated by your <hi>Prieſts,</hi> yet, we may be ſtill vnited in internall ſocietie with your <hi>Church,</hi> if you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine thoſe <hi>principles</hi> of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion ſound, and vnaltered, in the which our forefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers died, and (as we well <hi>hope</hi>) were ſaued.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pap.</speaker>
                  <p>How are you then gone from vs, if you be ſtill <hi>vnited</hi> with vs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                  <p>As the <hi>Prophets</hi> went from the corrupt Churches of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> and as <hi>Christ,</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles</hi> from the
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:2171:37"/> 
                     <hi>Scribes,</hi> and <hi>Phariſes, claman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do, &amp; diſſentiendo,</hi> by <hi>crying</hi> out againſt your corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and <hi>diſſenting</hi> from your innouations, and this<note n="a" place="margin">Caſ. conſult. pag. <hi>929.</hi> Gerſon. de p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3+ letters">
                           <desc>•••…</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate Eccleſiae.</note>your owne men allowed vs to doe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pap.</speaker>
                  <p>I, but ſome of your men ſay, that wee had no true Church of God in the Weſt of many yeeres before <hi>Luthers</hi> time.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                  <p>Their meaning is to be limited in reſpect of the <hi>Predominant,</hi> and preuai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling <hi>Faction.</hi> Your <hi>Church</hi> held (I confeſſe) a ſauing profeſſion of the Trueth of God, but your <hi>Church-men</hi> mingled therewith many
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:2171:37"/> damnable impieties. And theſe <hi>innouators</hi> onely carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the greateſt ſhew of the Church, are denied by our Writers to bee the true Church of God.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pap.</speaker>
                  <p>This it is we Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes obſerue. You dare not for all your malice deny the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> to haue in ſome ſort a <hi>ſauing profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> of the truth of God, but our <hi>Prieſts</hi> conclude direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that your Church hath <hi>no truth</hi> at all, and that<note n="a" place="margin">Barclaius paraeneſ. li. <hi>1.</hi> pag. <hi>7.</hi>
                     </note> none can be <hi>ſaued</hi> in that Church.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                  <p>As in euery king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome the <hi>generall eſtate</hi> is nothing ſo forward, actiue, quicke, and peremptorie, as
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:2171:38"/> the priuate <hi>Factions,</hi> and yet is found at the laſt more wiſe, and ſtayed in finall <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution:</hi> So in the Catholike Church, the<note n="b" place="margin">Can. loc. the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ol. l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi> Lindan. panopl. lib. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>7.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Factions</hi> are euer more headie, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipitate in their denunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations of <hi>Heauen,</hi> and <hi>Hell,</hi> then the <hi>maine body</hi> thereof. Hence it commeth to paſſe, that although the <hi>Greeke, Armenian, Ethiopian,</hi> and <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian,</hi> and (for the moſt part) the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> doth cenſure charitably of thoſe <hi>Laickes,</hi> who liuing rather <hi>In</hi> then <hi>Of</hi> the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> hold the <hi>grounds</hi> of the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Saluation, without any notorious <hi>mixtures,</hi>
                     <pb n="73" facs="tcp:2171:38"/> with the late ſuperſtitions, and impieties crept into the ſame; yet doth the<note n="a" place="margin">Quodlibet pag. <hi>342.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Papiſt,</hi> 
                     <note n="b" place="margin">Ruſſic. conun. c. <hi>23.</hi> p. <hi>103.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Ruſſeiſt,</hi>
                     <note n="c" place="margin">Sle. Hiſt. l. <hi>5.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Anabaptiſt,</hi> 
                     <note n="d" place="margin">Allens confeſ.</note> 
                     <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliſt,</hi> and<note n="e" place="margin">Proteſt. p. <hi>16.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Puritan</hi> hold no Church a Church of God, but his owne <hi>conuenticle,</hi> and all to bee damn'd, that are not of his ſocietie, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bination. Now what beliefe you ſhall affoord theſe <hi>Bou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſeux</hi> of the Catholike Church, that diſpoſe of <hi>Heauen,</hi> and <hi>Hell,</hi> as if it were their own <hi>Fee-ſimple,</hi> I leaue to your wiſdome and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon vnderſtanding.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pap.</speaker>
                  <p>Me thinks you now put me in minde of another obiection, which vſually we
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:2171:39"/> make againſt the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants of <hi>England</hi> that they bring in too much <hi>good fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip</hi> in religion, and make <hi>Saluation</hi> a flowre, which growes in euery mans gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den. Seeing that according to their <hi>Tenets, Papiſt, Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, Anabaptiſt,</hi> and <hi>Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>list,</hi> may euery one of them by meanes offered <hi>in his own Church,</hi> as a portion, or frag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the <hi>Catholike Church</hi> attaine vnto <hi>Saluation.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                  <p>If you were learned I could anſwere you in a word, that none of theſe three <hi>Sectories</hi> conſidered in his owne <hi>Formality, Qua talie,</hi> as he is a <hi>Papiſt, Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptist,</hi>
                     <pb n="75" facs="tcp:2171:39"/> or <hi>Familiſt</hi> can euer attaine vnto Saluation, but only as he is a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> man, admitted by <hi>Baptiſme</hi> vnto the viſible Church, &amp; there made partaker of <hi>Gods word,</hi> and <hi>Sacraments.</hi> For then (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though theſe bleſſed means are very much weakened, and obſcured in their Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues by the malice of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, and inuentions of men) yet may that holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that<note n="*" place="margin">Iohn 3.8.</note> 
                     <hi>bloweth where he li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth,</hi> worke in ſuch a mans heart by theſe weake inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, (and the rather, the more the Word is faithfully preached, and the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments be in thoſe places ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:2171:40"/> adminiſtred) a true <hi>faith</hi> in Chriſt Ieſus, to bring him to ſaluation. So then we doe not hold, that <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, Anabaptiſts,</hi> and <hi>Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts,</hi> but onely that ſome <hi>Chriſtians</hi> liuing in <hi>their</hi> congregations may (though with great difficultie in compariſon of this flouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing Church of ours, and theſe admirable meanes of <hi>Saluation</hi> tendered in the ſame) by the ſpeciall <hi>mercy</hi> of God be ſaued, and preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. If we be in an errour, it is ſafer to erre in <hi>Charity,</hi> then in <hi>Malice,</hi> and praeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitancie, conſidering the euent hereof is vnknowen to either of vs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:2171:40"/>
                  <speaker>Pap.</speaker>
                  <p>I but where was your Church before this <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation</hi> began?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                  <p n="1">1. When our Sauiour <hi>Chriſt</hi> with-drew the people from the<note n="a" place="margin">Matt. 16.12.</note> 
                     <hi>leauen</hi> of the Scribes, and Phariſees, to the bread,<note n="b" place="margin">Iohn 6.35.</note> 
                     <hi>which came down from heauen,</hi> and to ſaluation by faith in his Name, was it fitting to demaund of him, <hi>where his Church was before that Reformation?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. When theſe Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of<note n="c" place="margin">1. Corin. 5.1.</note> 
                     <hi>Corinth,</hi>
                     <note n="d" place="margin">Galat. 3.1.</note> 
                     <hi>Galatia,</hi> 
                     <note n="e" place="margin">Reuel. 2.12.</note> 
                     <hi>Pergamus,</hi> and<note n="f" place="margin">Reuel. 2.18.</note> 
                     <hi>Thiatyra,</hi> were full of abuſes, if ſome part onely vpon the preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Apoſtles had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed themſelues, and ſo a
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:2171:41"/> diuiſion had growen: would you ſtraight wayes haue tax't them of <hi>Nouelty,</hi> or ask't them <hi>where their Church had beene before this reformation?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3 When the Apoſtles caſt off <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he Lawe of <hi>Moſes,</hi> excepting only thoſe<note n="g" place="margin">Acts 15.29.</note> three or foure <hi>Ceremonies:</hi> and when the Primitiue church ſome hundred yeeres after, caſt off thoſe Ceremonies alſo (for I finde them brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of their laſt as it were about the times of<note n="h" place="margin">Anno <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>. <hi>140.</hi> Dialog. qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> inſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap>tur <hi>Tryphon.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Iustin Martyr</hi>) had it not beene a poore <hi>challenge</hi> of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> or <hi>Traskists</hi> of thoſe times, to demaund, <hi>where this vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceremoniall
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:2171:41"/> Church lay hid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the reformation?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I anſwer then, that our Church, before this <hi>refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation</hi> began, liued toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>in one communion</hi> with yours, with toleration of all thoſe <hi>abuſes,</hi> which you haue ſtill retained, and wee moſt iuſtly reiected.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pap.</speaker>
                  <p>I, but I hope you dare not compare in the gifts of the Spirit with <hi>Chriſt,</hi> his <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> or thoſe worthies of the <hi>primitiue</hi> Church. And therefore how preſumed you to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme</hi> your ſelues? Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, being a worke fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for a generall <hi>Councell</hi> to
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:2171:42"/> haue gone about, then for a ſmall handfull of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therne</hi> people.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Luther. in epiſt. ad Galat. in praefat. diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctio admiſſa in Comitijs Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanis ab ipſis Germanis Principibus. Scultet. annal. decad. <hi>1.</hi> pa. <hi>43.</hi>
                     </note>The <hi>Court</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> had ſo gained vpon the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> that is, the <hi>Pope,</hi> and his conclaue of <hi>Cardinals</hi> had wriggled in themſelues to that tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencie of power ouer the reſt of the <hi>Clergie,</hi> and well minded <hi>laity,</hi> that it appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red both at<note n="a" place="margin">In the yeere 1415.</note> 
                     <hi>Conſtance</hi>
                     <note n="b" place="margin">In the yeere 1546.</note> &amp; <hi>Trent,</hi> there was ſmall hope of <hi>Reformation</hi> from ſuch a Councell, where the <hi>Pope</hi> the <hi>partie</hi> to bee reformed, became the <hi>party reforming,</hi> and ſupreame <hi>Iudge,</hi> and preſident of the <hi>Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi>
                     <pb n="81" facs="tcp:2171:42"/> it ſelfe. Although poore ſeduced ignorant women are much caried away with the name of the Councell of <hi>Trent;</hi> yet you will quickly find out this ridiculous ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdity. In a generall <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell</hi> (as now it is held ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thence the decay of the <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire</hi>) the <hi>Pope</hi> is the <hi>party</hi> to be accuſed, yet puts vp his owne <hi>endictment,</hi> paſſeth a <hi>iury</hi> of his own <hi>vaſſals,</hi> and finde they what they will, being to giue finall iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, he will be ſure to do, as his ſuppoſed predeceſſor taught our Sauiour to doe, to wit, <hi>fauour himſelfe.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Matth. 16.22.</note> So as there was no hope of doing
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:2171:43"/> good by a Generall <hi>Councell,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">See the hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Councell of Trent.</note> vnles it were a <hi>generous</hi> and free <hi>Councell,</hi> and ſuch a one the <hi>Pope</hi> (you may bee ſure) would neuer abide.<note place="margin">Gerſon. de con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil. vnius obed.</note> And therefore one of your own writers concludes, that in ſuch a caſe, <hi>ſeuerall kingdomes</hi> are to reforme themſelues by <hi>National Councels,</hi> which England and Denmark did put in practiſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pap.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea, but it is too wel knowne, It was no zeale of <hi>Reformation,</hi> but carnall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, that mooued King <hi>Henry</hi> to touch vpon reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                  <p>To you (it ſeemes) it is giuen to know theſe <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets,</hi>
                     <pb n="83" facs="tcp:2171:43"/> but I ſee no reaſon we ſhould thinke ſo. The King could not bee induced to this <hi>reformation,</hi> as a meanes to poſſeſſe himſelfe of the <hi>Abbeies</hi> for they were <hi>already</hi> ſwallowed vp.<note place="margin">31. Henr. 8.</note> Nor as a preparatiue for his woing (as <hi>Saunders</hi> thinks) becauſe <hi>Fiſher</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Roche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster,</hi> who oppoſed his mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, made vp the one and twentieth prelate in baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Pope</hi> out of this Kingdome.<note place="margin">Inſtruction of a Chriſtian in the Preface.</note> But without doubt, the <hi>finger</hi> of God was the cauſe, whatſoeuer was the <hi>hint,</hi> or <hi>occaſion.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Act. 23.1.</note> 
                     <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus</hi> his popularitie, and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of <hi>pleaſing</hi> gaue S. <hi>Paul</hi>
                     <pb n="84" facs="tcp:2171:44"/> occaſion to <hi>appeale</hi> to <hi>Ceſar,</hi> and to viſite <hi>Rome,</hi> where, and when hee <hi>layd</hi> the firſt ſtone of the Romane church. Would you like it well a Proteſtant ſhould ſay, that your Church was founded vpon <hi>courtſhip</hi> and <hi>popularity?</hi> If any <hi>carnall</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, whetted on the king, that was but the <hi>opportunity,</hi> God onely was the <hi>first mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer,</hi> and prime <hi>Agent</hi> in this <hi>reformation.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pap.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay ſurely, God is the God of vnity, but your Church being once <hi>ſeuered</hi> from the Romane, was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently cantl'd out, into as many <hi>factions</hi> almoſt, as
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:2171:44"/> there are Countries; witnes the <hi>Lutherans</hi> ſoft and rigid, the <hi>Caluiniſts, Puritans, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitans, Brownists, Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts, &amp;c.</hi> So as one may ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily gueſſe, from what <hi>Ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma,</hi> and fenny ground this <hi>Hydra</hi> of ſo many heades had her firſt <hi>Originall.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                  <p>This argument ſounds very bigge in a la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies <hi>cloſet,</hi> and weighs much with the <hi>ignorant,</hi> and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned people, but with a man, but of a reaſonable vnderſtanding, this ſeeming <hi>diuiſion</hi> is no ſcandall at all to our <hi>reformed</hi> Churches. What man of any reading in the Hiſtories of the time,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:2171:45"/> but knowes well, that after the trumpet for this refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation had blowne, the firſt warning by<note n="a" place="margin">In the yeere 1375</note> 
                     <hi>Wicklef,</hi>
                     <note n="b" place="margin">In the yeere 1410.</note> 
                     <hi>Hus,</hi> and <hi>Hierome</hi> of <hi>Prage,</hi> and then the ſecond by<note n="c" place="margin">de ſignis ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. eccl.</note> 
                     <hi>Gerſon,</hi>
                     <note n="d" place="margin">1411.</note> 
                     <hi>Peter de A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaco,</hi>
                     <note n="e" place="margin">Bucholcer Anno <hi>1517.</hi>
                     </note> Cardinall <hi>Cuſanus,</hi>
                     <note n="f" place="margin">in Theor.</note> 
                     <hi>Picus Mirandula</hi>
                     <note n="g" place="margin">Phil. Comin. l. <hi>3.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Saua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norola,</hi> and many others, (of whom we reade in<note n="h" place="margin">Guic. hiſt. l. <hi>4.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Guic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiardyn</hi>) when<note n="i" place="margin">In the yeere 1512.</note> 
                     <hi>Luther</hi> in <hi>Germany</hi> blew the laſt, and that there appeared no hope of a free and indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent <hi>Councell,</hi> ſo as ſeuerall <hi>kingdomes</hi> were thus neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitated to prouide, and take care for themſelues, this <hi>worthy Act of Reformation,</hi>
                     <pb n="87" facs="tcp:2171:45"/> beginning in ſundry eſtates, by reaſon, partly of their <hi>diuers</hi> ſhapes, and <hi>formes of gouernements,</hi> and partly, of a great <hi>diſaduantage</hi> that one <hi>part</hi> of Chriſtendome, knew not, what <hi>another</hi> did, nor conſulted with their fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, that ſo they might with vnanimitie proceed in the ſame, did neceſſarily produce <hi>a ſeeming difference</hi> in the outward <hi>formes</hi> of particular Churches.</p>
                  <p>But loe, the goodneſſe, and <hi>prouidence</hi> of Almighty God. Although theſe Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches haue ſeuerall <hi>faces,</hi> yet haue they all but one <hi>heart,</hi> there being no <hi>eſſentiall, fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentall,</hi>
                     <pb n="88" facs="tcp:2171:46"/> or <hi>materiall</hi> diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence amongſt any of vs of the reformed Religion, as you may eaſily finde by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the <hi>confeſsions</hi> of our ſeueral churches. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for theſe odious Nick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>names of <hi>Lutheran, Caluinist, Huguenot, Zuinglian,</hi> and the like, be more ſparing of them, vntill you haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concil'd your own church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, as your <hi>Minorits,</hi> and <hi>Dominicans</hi> about the <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception</hi> of the bleſſed Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, your <hi>Ieſuits,</hi> and <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minicans</hi> about <hi>predeſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and thoſe dependant queſtions, your <hi>Sorboniſts,</hi> and <hi>Ieſuits</hi> about the boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:2171:46"/> and <hi>mereing out</hi> the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall, and Papall Authority: and you ſhall finde more <hi>doctrinall oppoſitions</hi> in your owne, then you can imagin in our Churches. But keepe you at home in your <hi>natiue</hi> countrey, and looke (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out enuie or partiali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie) vpon this flouriſhing Church of <hi>England,</hi> &amp; name me one Kingdom in all <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope</hi> that hath continued ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry neere this hundred yeres in that <hi>conſtancie,</hi> and <hi>immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tabilitie</hi> of doctrine or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline. Wee are ordered with that <hi>conſecration,</hi> that<note n="†" place="margin">Sand. de ſchiſ. Angl. lib. <hi>3.</hi>
                     </note> Archbiſhop<note n="‖" place="margin">32. <hi>of</hi> Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry 8.</note> 
                     <hi>Cranmer</hi> was, we renounce the Pope
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:2171:47"/> by that <hi>abiuration,</hi> that Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop <hi>Cranmer</hi> did, we <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe</hi> to thoſe <hi>Articles</hi> of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, which<note n="*" place="margin">In the yeere 1552.</note> Archbiſhop <hi>Cranmer</hi> in the Reformation pitch't vpon, before we can be admitted to any <hi>Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall</hi> function. Some wilde <hi>coults</hi> we haue, that ſtart, and boggle at the firſt, if they ſee but their owne ſhadowes, but by the <hi>diſcipline</hi> of the Church they are curb'd, and fetch't about againe, and taught in a little while to come on gently to this <hi>vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitie</hi> and <hi>ſubſcription.</hi> So that malice it ſelfe cannot challenge the Church of <hi>England,</hi> this moſt glorious
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:2171:47"/> portion of that Catholike Church, of any <hi>fractions,</hi> or <hi>diuiſions</hi> in points of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pap.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, but I haue of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten heard, that you haue no <hi>Biſhops</hi> or <hi>Priests</hi> at all in your Church. But that in the beginning of Q. <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beths</hi> raigne, <hi>lay-men</hi> in the <hi>Parliament</hi> did appoint you Biſhops, who conſecrated one another in a Tauerne at the<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Sander. de Schiſm. lib.</hi> 3. Harding a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Iewell.</note>
                     <hi>Nags-head</hi> in <hi>Cheapſide,</hi> and that your <hi>Priests</hi> were ordered onely by theſe Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liamentary Prelates.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                  <p>This tale of the <hi>Nags-head, Harding, Sanders,</hi> and <hi>Stapleton</hi> haue forged
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:2171:48"/> out of their owne Nagges-heads without any ground, or likelihood at all. And yet as eaſily as they came by it, it put a<note n="a" place="margin">M. Maſon Archdeacon of Suff.</note> 
                     <hi>Miniſter</hi> of our Church to an infinite deale of learned paines. Who by his Maieſties ſpeciall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, did ſearch out the auncient <hi>Records</hi> of the Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> (agnized ſithence by many <hi>Priests</hi> and <hi>Ieſuits,</hi> in the <hi>Clincke,</hi> and other priſons) and out of them hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed a <hi>learned booke,</hi> ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſucceſſiue <hi>Conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> of all the Biſhoppes of <hi>England,</hi> from that firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocation that<note n="b" place="margin">Inſtitut. of a Chriſtian. fol. <hi>19.</hi>
                     </note> baniſht the
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:2171:48"/> 
                     <hi>Pope</hi> about the yeere 1536, ſo as any <hi>Miniſter</hi> looking out that Biſhop, who gaue him <hi>Orders,</hi> may preſently aſcend in a right line of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops to thoſe Prelates, that liued in the raigne of <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth, before the <hi>refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation.</hi> And therfore if your owne <hi>Priests</hi> be lawfull, you may not quarrell with <hi>ours,</hi> differing onely from yours, in their renouncing of your impieties, and <hi>ſuperstiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pap.</speaker>
                  <p>This <hi>Record</hi> you ſpeake of, is ſomewhat to the purpoſe, vnleſſe the <hi>he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie</hi> of thoſe firſt Biſhops did diſable them for gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:2171:49"/> of lawfull <hi>Conſecrations,</hi> and <hi>Orders.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note n="c" place="margin">S. Baſil. Nazianz. S. Ambroſ. S. Hierom. S. Auſten: <hi>were in their times called heretiques.</hi> Lindan. panopl. lib. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>7.</hi>
                     </note>
                     <hi>Heretique</hi> indeed, is a common word for vs, in the mouth of euery wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, that is but a little <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manized.</hi> But is it not ſtrange how<note n="d" place="margin">Inſtitut. of a Chriſtian, fol. <hi>18</hi>
                     </note> he ſhould be an <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retique,</hi> that ſayes the <hi>Creed,</hi> and the <hi>Lords prayer</hi> in that literall, and explicite <hi>ſenſe,</hi> and meaning, that all the <hi>Fathers</hi> of the Church for the firſt 500. yeeres vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood the ſame? Yet this is nothing to the point in hand. For firſt, if the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> time were lawfull, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their being conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:2171:49"/> by <hi>Cranmer,</hi> and other <hi>tainted</hi> Biſhops (as you terme them) why may not the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops in Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and King <hi>Iames</hi> his time, expect the ſame priuiledge? And ſecondly, your <hi>owne</hi>
                     <note n="e" place="margin">Dominic. a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Soto. in <hi>4.</hi> Sent. d. <hi>25.</hi> Biel. in <hi>4</hi> d. <hi>25.</hi> q. <hi>1.</hi> Con. <hi>4.</hi> Capreol, in <hi>4.</hi> d. <hi>25.</hi> q. <hi>1.</hi> art. <hi>3.</hi> &amp;c.</note> Writers confeſſe, that <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie</hi> (which we ſuppoſe, but not yeeld theſe Prelates fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len vnto) cannot raſe out from that <hi>Character</hi> of a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, this inſeparable power of <hi>conſecrating,</hi> and <hi>orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pap.</speaker>
                  <p>Yet there remaines an obiection againſt your <hi>Church,</hi> that it cannot poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly be a true Church, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is <hi>ſeuered</hi> from the
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:2171:50"/> true viſible <hi>head</hi> thereof the <hi>Pope</hi> of <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                  <p>This is a ſtale ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection, and ſoone anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. The church of<note n="f" place="margin">Euſeb. li. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>23.</hi> Eraſ. epiſt. in Agrippa de vanit. c. <hi>59.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Aſia</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered from Pope <hi>Victor</hi> in the yeere 200.<note n="g" place="margin">Baron. tom. <hi>3.</hi> ad ann. <hi>375.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> and his fellowes from <hi>Faelix</hi> and <hi>Tiberius</hi> in the yere 375,<note n="h" place="margin">Euſeb. l. <hi>7.</hi> c. <hi>2. 3. 4.</hi> Caſian. conſult. art. <hi>7.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Cyprian,</hi> and his brethren, yea and three <hi>National Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels</hi> from Pope <hi>Stephen,</hi> in the yeere 250,<note n="i" place="margin">Bellar. de Ro. Pont. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>25.</hi> &amp; <hi>46.</hi> Lindan. panopl. l. <hi>7.</hi> c. <hi>89.</hi> Poſsevinus in Apparat. titul. Carthag.</note> the Biſhops of <hi>Carthage</hi> Schiſmatized from all Popes of <hi>Rome</hi> for an hundred yeres together, about the yeere 409. laſtly<note n="k" place="margin">Bellar. de Ro. Pont. <hi>l. 2.</hi> c. <hi>31.</hi> Idem de Matri. c. <hi>15.</hi> art. <hi>2.</hi>
                     </note> the <hi>Greeke</hi> Church cut off from the <hi>Roman</hi> for 300. yeeres, are ſufficient teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:2171:50"/> there may be a <hi>true</hi> Church of God, though <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> and diuided from the <hi>Pope</hi> of <hi>Rome.</hi> And here in this kingdome it was no Proteſtant, but <hi>Popiſh</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, that concluded in a <hi>Nationall</hi> Synode,<note n="l" place="margin">Institut. of a Chriſtian, ſet foorth <hi>anno 1537.</hi> by Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority.</note> our King might (if he pleaſed) create a <hi>Pope of his owne</hi> in his own kingdoms, and dominions, and yet remaine a member of the Catholike Church.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pap.</speaker>
                  <p>Well the beſt is you haue beene ſo tedious in your anſweres, that I haue (I thank God) forgotten all, that you haue ſaid for your <hi>reformed</hi> Church.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                  <p>But I will helpe that
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:2171:51" rendition="simple:additions"/> quickly by ſumming vp of all into theſe 12. <hi>Poſitions:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1 We haue a <hi>Church,</hi> as hauing
<list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Doctrine.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Saluation.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Diſcipline.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2 It is a <hi>portion</hi> of the Catholique Church.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. It hath a <hi>Spirituall</hi> v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of doctrine with the <hi>vntainted</hi> members of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4 And yet hath <hi>ſeuered</hi> her ſelfe from the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> by crying againſt, and <hi>diſſenting</hi> from her <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtions.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5 Which <hi>ſome</hi> of vs hold no true Church of Gods, in regard of the <hi>preuailing</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <pb n="99" facs="tcp:2171:51"/>6 Although we iudge <hi>charitably</hi> of the Saluation of <hi>ſome</hi> in that Church.</p>
                  <p n="7">7 Who notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding are ſaued not as <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts,</hi> but as <hi>Christians.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="8">8 And in one <hi>lumpe,</hi> or <hi>communion</hi> with this Church liued <hi>ours</hi> before the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation.</p>
                  <p n="9">9 Which then for want of a <hi>Generall,</hi> did ſeuer her ſelfe, by a <hi>Nationall</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, from the ſame.</p>
                  <p n="10">10 Nor was it any <hi>by-re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect</hi> of the Kings, but God, and the <hi>cry of that age,</hi> that cauſed this <hi>reformation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="11">11 Nor doe our refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Churches <hi>diſſent</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:2171:52"/> themſelues in <hi>do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,</hi> but in outward <hi>poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,</hi> and <hi>diſcipline</hi> onely.</p>
                  <p n="12">12 Our <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Prieſts</hi> come by a lineall <hi>Succeſsion</hi> from <hi>Henry</hi> the eights time, nor can a ſuppoſall of <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie</hi> cut off this deſcent.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 2.</hi> Of the Scriptures.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pap.</speaker>
                  <p>DOe you then hold this <hi>Church</hi> of yours to bee the ground of your <hi>Faith,</hi> and reaſon of your <hi>beleeuing,</hi> So as you doe therefore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:2171:52"/> all the points of your ſaluation to be true, becauſe the <hi>Church</hi> doeth teach, and inſtruct you in the ſame? Or haue you any other <hi>rule,</hi> and <hi>ground</hi> of your faith?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                  <p>The <hi>Authority,</hi> and good conceipt we haue of Gods <hi>Church</hi>
                     <note n="a" place="margin">Auguſt. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Epiſtol. fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam. c. <hi>5.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>prepareth</hi> vs to beleeue the points of our Saluation, and ſerueth as an <hi>introduction</hi> to bring vs to the <hi>diſcerning,</hi> and perfect apprehenſion of theſe my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of our <hi>faith,</hi> but the <hi>Scripture</hi> onely is the <hi>ground,</hi> and <hi>reaſon</hi> of our beleeuing. For as the<note n="b" place="margin">Iohn 4.29.</note> 
                     <hi>Samaritans</hi> were induced, and drawne on to beleeue in <hi>Chriſt</hi> by that talk
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:2171:53"/> of the <hi>woman,</hi> but hauing heard <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe plainely, they <hi>beleeue no longer for her ſaying, but</hi>
                     <note n="c" place="margin">Iohn 4.42.</note> 
                     <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they heard him ſpeake himſelfe:</hi> So doe we <hi>beginne</hi> to beleeue; moued thus to doe, by the <hi>good conceipt</hi> we haue of the <hi>Church,</hi> but reſt not in it, as the ground of our beleeuing, but onely in the infallible aſſurance of Gods truth in the booke of <hi>Scriptures.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pap.</speaker>
                  <p>Then God helpe you, if that be your laſt <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution.</hi> For our <hi>Church</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not <hi>erre,</hi> but your <hi>Scriptures</hi> without the helpe of the <hi>Church,</hi> to tell you ſo much,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:2171:53"/> can neuer bee aſcertained vnto you, to be the word of <hi>God;</hi> And therefore what aſſuredneſſe of beleefe can you propoſe your ſelues vpon ſo vnſetled a <hi>founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                  <p>The Catholike Church indeed,<note place="margin">Wald. doctr. fid. l. <hi>2.</hi> art. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>27.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>spread ouer the world,</hi> cannot erre <hi>dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably,</hi> though the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and all other <hi>particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la</hi> Churches, may, as your owne <hi>Writers</hi> confeſſe. But the <hi>Scriptures</hi> wee know to be the word of God, not becauſe the Church, or <hi>Churchmen,</hi> doe tell vs ſo much, but by the <hi>Authority of God himſelfe,</hi>
                     <note n="a" place="margin">Caluin inſtit. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>7.</hi> d. <hi>4.</hi>
                     </note> whom we
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:2171:54"/> doe moſt certainely <hi>diſcerne</hi> to ſpeake in his word, when it is preached vnto vs. For if we bring pure eyes, and perfect ſenſes, the maieſtie of God forthwith, preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it ſelfe vnto vs in the holy <hi>Scriptures,</hi> and beating downe all thoughts of <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicting,</hi> or <hi>doubting</hi> things ſo heauenly, forceth our hearts to yeeld <hi>aſſent,</hi> and obedience vnto the ſame. And therefore if you <hi>doubt</hi> whether that which you reade in your <hi>Bible</hi> be the word of <hi>God,</hi> or finde any <hi>reluctancy</hi> in your vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding to the doctrine of the ſame, it is in vaine to flie
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:2171:54"/> vnto either <hi>Church,</hi> or <hi>Churchmen,</hi> to be perſwaded in this point, but down vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your <hi>knees,</hi> and pray fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uently vnto <hi>God</hi> for <hi>Faith,</hi> and the illumination of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> which can on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aſſure you of the trueth of the <hi>Scriptures.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Caluin. inſtit. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>7.</hi> diſt. <hi>5.</hi>
                     </note> For after wee are enlightned by the <hi>Spirit,</hi> we do no longer <hi>truſt</hi> either our <hi>owne</hi> iudgement, or the iudgement of <hi>other</hi> men, or of the <hi>Church,</hi> that the <hi>Scriptures</hi> are of <hi>God,</hi> but aboue all certainety of <hi>hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane iudgement,</hi> wee moſt certainely <hi>reſolue,</hi> as if in them wee ſaw the maieſtie and glory of God, that by
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:2171:55"/> the miniſterie of men they came vnto vs from <hi>Gods</hi> owne moſt ſacred mouth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pap.</speaker>
                  <p>But what certaine <hi>ground</hi> of faith can you place on the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> ſeeing by the <hi>ſeuerall</hi> interpretations of men and women they are turned and wreſted like <hi>a noſe of wax</hi> to euerie pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate deſigne and purpoſe? Doe not you obſerue how the <hi>Catholikes, Proteſtants,</hi> and eſpeciallie the <hi>Brow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nists,</hi> and <hi>Anabaptists,</hi> doe fit <hi>all</hi> their turnes out of the holie <hi>Scriptures?</hi> on which of theſe ſenſes, and imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations is your faith roo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted? or peraduenture, haue
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:2171:55"/> you ſome odde <hi>capritchious</hi> kinde of interpretation of your <hi>owne</hi> apprehenſion to direct you in theſe buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                  <p>Wee <hi>lay-folkes</hi> are licenſed in the Church of <hi>England</hi> to <hi>reade,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Doe all inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prete. 1. Cor. 12.30.</note> but not to <hi>interprete</hi> Scriptures, excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting onely thoſe paſſages, which containe the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie points of our <hi>Saluation,</hi> the which paſſages are ſo plaine, &amp; <hi>eaſie</hi> euery where, that any <hi>man,</hi> or <hi>woman</hi> of the meaneſt capacitie (eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciallie if he, or ſhe be inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in their <hi>Catechiſme</hi> or grounds of religion) may perfectly conceiue,<note place="margin">Staplet. cont. <hi>6.</hi> q. <hi>7.</hi> exp. ſi art.</note> and <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand</hi>
                     <pb n="108" facs="tcp:2171:56"/> them. But for the harder and more <hi>difficult</hi> places, we leaue them to be interpreted by our <hi>Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> in their <hi>Sermons,</hi> and dailie miniſterie. For the ordering of which inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretations, there are (as I haue beene told) 10. ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall <hi>helps,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Obſerued out of D. Field, M. Hooker, Chemnitius, and Trelca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius.</note> the which if they be followed wil be ſure, and vnfallible <hi>guides,</hi> to bolt out the true meaning of each place of Scripture.</p>
                  <p>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 <hi>An illumination of the vnderſtanding by the Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2 <hi>A minde free from other thoughts, and deſirous of the truth.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <pb n="109" facs="tcp:2171:56" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                        <item>3 <hi>Knowledge of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, Creedes, Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſmes, Principles, and other Axiomes of Diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>4 <hi>A conſiderations how our meaning ſuites with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther points of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>5 <hi>The weighing of circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, antecedents, and conſequents.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>6 <hi>Knowledge of Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, Arts, and Sciences.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>7 <hi>Continuall reading, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditating, and praying.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>8 <hi>Ioint, and vniarring expoſitions of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>9 <hi>Conſenting decrees of <add>auncient</add>
                              <pb n="110" facs="tcp:2171:57"/> Synods, and Councels.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>10 <hi>Knowledge in the tongues.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>Becauſe therefore lay-men, and women, Papiſts, Browniſts, and Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts, are wanting in <hi>all,</hi> or <hi>ſome</hi> of theſe helpes, they bring foorth many times ſuch lame, and <hi>prodigious</hi> interpretations.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pap.</speaker>
                  <p>If wee make the <hi>Scripture,</hi> &amp; not the Church the rule of our <hi>Faith,</hi> how ſhall we beleeue, the <hi>Creed,</hi> the <hi>Trinity,</hi> the <hi>Sacraments,</hi> the <hi>vnity</hi> of <hi>Eſſence,</hi> the three <hi>perſons</hi> in the Deity, &amp;c. words neuer read in the <hi>Bible,</hi> and yet neceſſarily to
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:2171:57"/> be apprehended of vs vpon paine of <hi>damnation?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſay that all theſe things are ſet downe in Scriptures, either in <hi>ſo many ſyllables,</hi> or at leaſtwiſe by neceſſarie <hi>inferences,</hi> and <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductions.</hi> And wee doe not therefore beleeue them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are onely taught by the <hi>Church,</hi> but becauſe they are rooted and groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the holie <hi>Scriptures,</hi> the onelie ſtay and <hi>pillar</hi> of our affiance.</p>
               </sp>
               <div type="summary">
                  <head>To ſumme vp therefore all this Chapter,</head>
                  <p n="1">1 The Church doeth <hi>prepare</hi> vs, but the <hi>Scripture</hi> onely doeth force vs to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb n="112" facs="tcp:2171:58"/>2 The whole Church cannot, any part thereof may erre damnablie.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Wee are taught the Scriptures to bee the word of God by the <hi>Holy Ghoſt, mouing</hi> in our hearts, and not by the Church <hi>ſounding</hi> in our eares.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 <hi>Lay-men</hi> are to reade, not to <hi>interprete</hi> Scriptures.</p>
                  <p n="5">5 The miſſe of ſome <hi>rules</hi> cauſeth wrong <hi>expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> of Scriptures.</p>
                  <p n="6">6 <hi>All</hi> things neceſſary to bee beleeued are either found <hi>in,</hi> or collected and inferred <hi>from</hi> the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:2171:58"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 3.</hi> Of Iuſtification.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pap.</speaker>
                  <p>HOW then doe you learne out of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, that you are to be <hi>iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified,</hi> and ſaued before God?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                  <p>I am to bee <hi>iustified</hi> before God, by an Act <hi>ſingle</hi> in it ſelfe, but <hi>double</hi> in our apprehenſion, which is, By Gods <hi>not imputing</hi> vnto me my ſinnes, and the ſame Gods <hi>imputing</hi> vnto mee Chriſts righteouſneſſe, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:2171:59"/> by his creating of <hi>faith</hi> in my heart by the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> to aſſure my Soule that God, for the <hi>Actiue</hi> and <hi>Paſſiue</hi> obedience of Chriſt Ieſus hath accompliſhed thoſe two former Actes, of <hi>not imputing</hi> my Sinne, and of <hi>imputing</hi> vnto mee Chriſts righteouſneſſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pap.</speaker>
                  <p>A verie <hi>eaſie,</hi> no doubt, and reaſonable religion, which you haue learned out of the <hi>Scriptures.</hi> Heere is no burthen left for your <hi>owne</hi> backe, you caſt all vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Chriſts</hi> ſhoulders by the meanes of theſe two fine wordes, <hi>Not imputing,</hi> and <hi>imputing,</hi> and a third ſwim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:2171:59"/> notion of your own conceipt (which any man may haue with a little ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gining) termed by you <hi>faith,</hi> it would be knowne there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, where your Church hath found out theſe words of <hi>Art,</hi> in the holie <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                  <p>We do in all humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie confeſſe, that the globe of our <hi>ſinnes,</hi> and the world of that <hi>righteouſneſſe,</hi> which is to appeare in the preſence of <hi>Gods Iustice,</hi> is too maſſie for vs to ſuſtaine, that are but duſt and aſhes, and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portable only by that <hi>Atlas,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Verba Lutheri ep. ad Henr. <hi>8.</hi> tom. <hi>2.</hi> ep. p. <hi>290.</hi>
                     </note> Chriſt Ieſus, vpon whoſe ſhoulders, not our conceits,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:2171:60"/> but the <hi>goodnes</hi> of God hath plac't and preſſed them. But that theſe wordes <hi>imputing,</hi> and <hi>not imputing,</hi> are ſuch <hi>Greeke</hi> vnto <hi>you,</hi> I doe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute it to your not reading of <hi>Scriptures,</hi> and taking vp your religion by <hi>truſt,</hi> and credit from ſuch <hi>Fripperers,</hi> and <hi>Brokers,</hi> as by lending your ſoules, a falſe opinion of <hi>merits</hi> and <hi>good workes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> do diue into your <hi>purſes,</hi> and eat vp your <hi>estates,</hi> by way of <hi>interest.</hi> Not to trouble you (as I might) with a thouſand places, aske <hi>Dauid,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 32.1.</note> whether <hi>not imputing of ſin,</hi> and S. <hi>Paul,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 4.45.</note> whether the <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puting</hi> of Chriſts righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:2171:60"/> doth not make vs <hi>bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,</hi> and <hi>iuſtified.</hi> For the <hi>words</hi> vſe your owne eyes, and inſpection. And for the <hi>meaning,</hi> I referre you to<note n="a" place="margin">August. tom. <hi>8</hi> in pſalm. <hi>31.</hi>
                     </note> S. <hi>Auguſtines</hi> vpon the one, and<note n="b" place="margin">Amb. in ep. ad Rom. c. <hi>8.</hi>
                     </note> S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentarie vpon the other paſſage. Now that you fondlie imagine, that <hi>Faith,</hi> this heauenly hand, that <hi>reacheth</hi> at this double Act, and <hi>applies</hi> it to our owne Soules, is ſuch an apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, as you may command, when you pleaſe out of your owne phantaſie, it is ſuch a poore opinion, that no Soule, warmed with the leaſt touch or feeling of <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi>
                     <pb n="118" facs="tcp:2171:61"/> but contemnes with a moſt holie ſcorne, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach. I tell you, (and if you once haue it, your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience will tell you no leſſe) this <hi>Faith</hi> is the rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt iewell in Gods cabinet,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.8.</note> and can neuer be compas'd by any endeuour of ours, vntill the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> comes downe from heauen to ſet, and enchaſe it in our <hi>hearts</hi> with his owne fingers as it were. And being once ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, it new moldes, and faſhions the whole nature of man, ſo as the <hi>vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding</hi> becomes more enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to know <hi>God,</hi> the <hi>will</hi> to obey God, the <hi>affections,</hi>
                     <pb n="119" facs="tcp:2171:61"/> to loue God, and our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren. Nor can it bee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued (to the comfort of our conſcience) without daily <hi>praying, meditating,</hi> do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>good workes,</hi> reading the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> hearing good <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons,</hi> and peruſing of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout, and godly <hi>Treatiſes.</hi> My beliefe therefore is this: Gods <hi>not imputing of ſinne, and imputing of righteouſneſſe</hi> is the <hi>worker,</hi> The <hi>Merits of Chriſt</hi> the <hi>procurer, Faith</hi> wrought by the holy Ghoſt the <hi>inſtrument,</hi> or applier, good <hi>workes,</hi> or my inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent <hi>righteouſneſſe</hi> (poore as it is) a <hi>conſequent</hi> onely, <hi>ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect,</hi> and <hi>follower,</hi> of my <hi>iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="120" facs="tcp:2171:62"/>
                  <speaker>Pap.</speaker>
                  <p>I haue heard ſome of your ſide, raile againſt the very name of <hi>inherent righteouſneſſe,</hi> which you ſeem now to acknowledge, &amp; embrace. Do <hi>Proteſtants</hi> therefore challenge any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>righteouſneſſe,</hi> beſides that of Chriſts, which is <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                  <p>They doe acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge a <hi>Sanctification,</hi> or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent righteouſnes, in the ſame ſence as the auncient <hi>Fathers</hi> tooke the Word, but not as <hi>Ieſuits</hi> of late miſtake it. We haue righteouſneſſe <hi>inherent,</hi> or ſubſiſting in vs, according to the which we ſhall be <hi>iudged,</hi> but not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:2171:62"/> to the which wee ſhall be <hi>iustified.</hi> You make your righteouſneſſe to goe <hi>before</hi> as the <hi>cauſe;</hi> we ours, to come <hi>after,</hi> as the <hi>effect</hi> of <hi>Iustification.</hi> You ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe yours ſo <hi>abſolute</hi> as to <hi>euict</hi> from God; all wee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect from ours, is, but to <hi>te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stifie</hi> vnto men, that we are <hi>iuſtified.</hi> You bragge of a perfection of <hi>degrees,</hi> wee onely teach a perfection of <hi>parts</hi> in our <hi>righteouſneſſe.</hi> For as in the dawning of the day, euery part of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens is enlightened, though none as yet in a <hi>full,</hi> and compleat ſplendour: ſo af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Act of <hi>Iustification,</hi>
                     <pb n="122" facs="tcp:2171:63"/> apprehended by <hi>faith,</hi> euery facultie of the ſoule is <hi>ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified,</hi> and made righteous, the <hi>vnderſtanding,</hi> the <hi>will,</hi> the <hi>affections,</hi> the <hi>thoughts,</hi> the <hi>words,</hi> the <hi>deedes,</hi> but none of thoſe, <hi>ſo</hi> exactly perfect, as to <hi>implead</hi> a Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication at the throne of God. We therfore waue off this <hi>little</hi> righteouſneſſe of our owne, as a piece of<note n="*" place="margin">Eſay 64.6.</note> 
                     <hi>pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted cloth</hi> in the Act of our Iuſtification, and caſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor onely vpon the <hi>merits</hi> of Chriſt. But according to your Doctrine of<note n="*" place="margin">Concil. Trid.</note> 
                     <hi>infuſed Charitie,</hi> not the Almighty <hi>reconciled,</hi> but the man <hi>qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified,</hi> not Chriſt <hi>patient,</hi> but
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:2171:63"/> an habite <hi>inherent,</hi> not God by grace <hi>pardoning,</hi> but an inſtilled vertue (like a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt of <hi>Mithridate</hi>) expel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſinne, is the cauſe of your <hi>Iustification.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pap.</speaker>
                  <p>But haue you any vſe of your <hi>Free-wil</hi> in either righteouſnes; I meane that <hi>imputed,</hi> or this <hi>inherent?</hi> Or are you (as ſome relate your opinions) meerely <hi>ſuffering,</hi> and <hi>paſsiue,</hi> like ſo many ſtockes, and ſtones, caſting not ſo much as a ſigh, grone, or ſhort wiſh, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards this great worke of your <hi>conuerſion?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                  <p>In our firſt <hi>conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> to be righteous, and the
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:2171:64"/> Act of our <hi>Iuſtification,</hi> wee are like ſo many <hi>Niobes,</hi> or images of marble, which moue not at all, but as they are, in the whole <hi>lumpe,</hi> car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and tranſported; Our vnderſtandings not affoor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding themſelues the leaſt glymps of <hi>knowledge,</hi> nor our wils, the leaſt ſhew of <hi>inclination</hi> vnto this Act, but as they are either of them powerfully bended by the <hi>Holy Ghost</hi> to lay holde by <hi>Faith</hi> on this <hi>imputed righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe.</hi> But in our ſecond <hi>conuerſion</hi> to be more righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, which we call the Act of our <hi>Sanctification,</hi> wee moue like<note n="*" place="margin">Ariſt. polit. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Daedalus</hi> his ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:2171:64"/> or pageants vpon wheeles, dull, and vnweldy in <hi>our owne</hi> natures, but ſo quickened, and enliued by thoſe engines of <hi>Grace,</hi> and <hi>motions of the holy Ghoſt</hi> in our ſoules, and conſciences, that now our vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, wils, and affections doe <hi>cooperate,</hi> and runne along, with the <hi>Grace</hi> of God in all our <hi>workes</hi> of pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and deuotion. To that <hi>imputed</hi> righteouſneſſe ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we haue no freeneſſe, or <hi>cooperation</hi> of our Willes: to our <hi>inherent</hi> righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe we haue. Wee haue no <hi>concurrance</hi> in that <hi>firſt</hi> Act of our Iuſtification, but
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:2171:65"/> we haue a cooperation of the will (rouzed vp, and <hi>excited</hi> by grace) in all <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent</hi> Acts of our <hi>Sanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</hi> The points therfore of this Chapter are theſe:
<list>
                        <item>1. <hi>Iuſtification</hi> conſiſts, in Gods <hi>not imputing</hi> of Sinne, and in his <hi>impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> of <hi>Christs</hi> righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe vnto vs.</item>
                        <item>2. It is not our <hi>conceipt,</hi> but the iuſtice, and <hi>mercy</hi> of God, which layes this loade on our Sauiour <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>3. Whoſoeuer is acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the <hi>Scripture,</hi> cannot be vnacquainted
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:2171:65"/> with <hi>imputed righteouſnes.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>4. <hi>Imputed righteouſneſſe</hi> is ſoone apprehended, but infuſed <hi>Faith,</hi> muſt bee firſt obtained.</item>
                        <item>5. We haue an <hi>inherent</hi> righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, which is the <hi>effect,</hi> but none, which is the <hi>cauſe</hi> of our Iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</item>
                        <item>6. <hi>Grace</hi> alone works our <hi>iuſtification; Grace,</hi> and <hi>we</hi> together (but <hi>wee</hi> in the ſecond place) our <hi>Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:2171:66"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 4.</hi> Of Saints, Soules of the Dead, and thoſe dependant questions.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pap.</speaker>
                  <p>WEe are ſcandali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed likewiſe at your Church, becauſe you giue no more reuerence to the <hi>Saints</hi> then you doe, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>praying</hi> vnto them, nor adorning their <hi>images,</hi> nor giuing them any ſet im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment aboue in <hi>heauen,</hi> or the leaſt care of vs here on <hi>earth.</hi> Which ſmels ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much of the hereſies of
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:2171:66"/> the<note n="a" place="margin">Epiphan.</note> 
                     <hi>Cainans,</hi> and <hi>Eunomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> condemned ſo many yeeres agone in the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Church.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                  <p>What employment the <hi>Saints</hi> haue in heauen, beſides the contemplation of God <hi>face to face,</hi>
                     <note n="b" place="margin">Hugo de S. V. l. <hi>2.</hi> de Sacram. c. <hi>11.</hi> Al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>iſ. l. <hi>3.</hi>
                     </note>we <hi>know not,</hi> nor doe<note n="c" place="margin">Caſsand. in conſult. art. <hi>21.</hi>
                     </note> we <hi>deny</hi> their praying for vs. Vpon earth they receiue in <hi>our</hi> Church, all that honour beſpoken for them in the <hi>primitiue</hi> Church. Wee keepe duely the <hi>memorials</hi> of the bleſſed <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgine,</hi> and the twelue <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles,</hi> and a yeerely pane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyricall commemoration of <hi>all</hi> the Martyrs, &amp; <hi>Saints</hi> of God: reſpecting them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:2171:67"/> our<note n="d" place="margin">Auguſt. contr. Fauſt. l. <hi>20.</hi> c. <hi>2.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>fellowes</hi> and <hi>friends,</hi> though not as our<note n="e" place="margin">Iouius hiſt. lib. <hi>24.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Tutelar gods,</hi> and young little Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours. We admire their liues, and as we doe not furiouſly <hi>deface,</hi> ſo doe we not <hi>adore</hi> their images. Becauſe<note n="f" place="margin">August. in Pſal. <hi>113.</hi>
                     </note> S. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> would faine know, where that Chriſtian may be found, that <hi>prayeth</hi> or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doreth, <hi>beholding</hi> an image.<note n="g" place="margin">Idem de ciuit. Dei. lib. <hi>22.</hi> cap. <hi>10.</hi>
                     </note> We reare them no <hi>Temples,</hi> as to Gods, but trophees onely of <hi>praiſe,</hi> as to deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing men.<note n="h" place="margin">Epi. ad Hebr. cap. <hi>11.</hi>
                     </note> S. <hi>Paul</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe did all this, and hee did no more. We dignifie them as Saints by <hi>celebration,</hi> wee dare not <hi>deifie</hi> them, as Gods by <hi>inuocation.</hi> Your<note n="i" place="margin">Eckius in his Enchirid.</note> 
                     <hi>owne</hi>
                     <pb n="131" facs="tcp:2171:67"/> men confeſſe, there is for this praying to Saints nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>precept</hi> nor <hi>example</hi> in all the <hi>Bible.</hi> And<note n="1" place="margin">Orig. l. <hi>2.</hi> in Epiſt. ad Rom.</note> 
                     <hi>Origen</hi> made but a queſtion,<note n="2" place="margin">Baſil. cited by the Biſhop of Lincolne.</note> S. <hi>Baſil</hi> an <hi>If,</hi>
                     <note n="3" place="margin">NaZ. Orat. <hi>1.</hi> in Iulian<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; orat. in Gorgon.</note> 
                     <hi>Gregory Nazian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zene</hi> a <hi>thinking,</hi> or an <hi>opinion</hi> onely of this, which you make an <hi>Article</hi> of Faith. We are commanded to call vpon<note n="4" place="margin">Pſal. 50 15.</note> 
                     <hi>God,</hi> vpon him<note n="5" place="margin">Matth. 4.10.</note> 
                     <hi>one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> for he is our<note n="6" place="margin">Pſal. 74.12.</note> 
                     <hi>King of old,</hi> and we are ſtarke mad if we thinke to better our ſelues by changing of <hi>Maſters.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pap.</speaker>
                  <p>I, but how will you anſwere <hi>Antiquitie:</hi> For I haue beene told, that there are found in the writings of the Auncient <hi>Fathers,</hi> pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:2171:68"/> made to many of the <hi>Saints</hi> and holy men <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                  <p>If you pleaſe to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue them well, you ſhall finde, they are no <hi>Oriſons,</hi> but <hi>Orations.</hi> A certain kind of paſſionate, and rhetori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call <hi>exclamations</hi> made vnto the dead, concerning ſome <hi>notable</hi> euents happened vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Church in generall, or the parties themſelues in particular. This is eaſily beleeued of them, who vſe to reade the Greeke <hi>Fathers,</hi> which are full of ſuch <hi>eiacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations</hi> in their affectionate Diſcourſes. And that their paſſages, are <hi>no prayers,</hi> this
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:2171:68"/> is an argument.<note n="1" place="margin">Elienſ. reſp. ad Apolog. pag. <hi>42.</hi>
                     </note> Becauſe there is not any of all theſe <hi>Fathers,</hi> when they treat of <hi>prayer,</hi> (as it is their vſuall theme) of ſet purpoſe, and handle all the <hi>obiects,</hi> and <hi>kindes</hi> therof, that euer men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion one ſyllable of this <hi>prayer</hi> to <hi>Saints.</hi> This is an anſwere will neuer be taken away by any of your ſide. Now if your Prieſts tooke an <hi>hint</hi> hereby, to erect <hi>Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> for the<note n="2" place="margin">Vide Epiſt. Vratiſlauienſ. apud S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>lte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, Annal. decad. <hi>1.</hi> p. <hi>150</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>dead,</hi> I hope you know they looſe nothing by the bargaine.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pap.</speaker>
                  <p>You likewiſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne, and deride the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques</hi> of the Saints, which are ſhewed, preſerued, and
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:2171:69" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
                     <hi>adored</hi> in our Churches.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                  <p>We are ſo farre from <hi>contemning</hi> any thing in this kinde, that did wee knowe them to bee true reliques, and no <hi>impoſtures,</hi> we ſhould honour them more then you doe, to wit,<note n="1" place="margin">K. Iames pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face monit.</note> with an honourable, and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian <hi>buriall.</hi> Wee heare indeed that there were of old<note n="2" place="margin">August. de moribus Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiae.</note> ſome Chriſtians that attributed <hi>too much</hi> to the reliques of the <hi>Martyrs,</hi> but we heare from the ſame <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi>
                     <note n="3" place="margin">Auguſt. de ciuit. Dei, l. <hi>8.</hi> cap. <hi>27.</hi>
                     </note> The better ſort of Chriſtians did <hi>not ſo.</hi> And we hold it very idle to<note n="4" place="margin">Plin. Sec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> l. <hi>4.</hi> ep. <hi>8.</hi>
                     </note> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe for our <hi>imitation</hi> any other, then the beſt, and
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:2171:69"/> moſt abſolute <hi>patterne.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pap.</speaker>
                  <p>You do alſo ſpeake baſely of the <hi>bleſſed virgin,</hi> and compare her to your <hi>owne</hi> wiues, and ſuch bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gages.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                  <p>A rayling French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man doth charge <hi>Melanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thon</hi> with ſuch a compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,<note place="margin">Florim. Remond en ſon Histoir ex Hom. Mel. in euang. de in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnat.</note> but that booke or paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage hee cites, is not to bee found among the <hi>workes</hi> of that moſt learned and <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt</hi> writer: Howeuer, our Church hath neuer a<note n="*" place="margin">Rogers in art. <hi>22.</hi>
                     </note> Saint <hi>Ruffyn</hi> (as yours hath) to heale all <hi>frenzies,</hi> and mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, and we count no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of thoſe deſperate ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, that any one ſhall vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:2171:70"/> againſt the glorious <hi>vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin.</hi> Yet I thinke your men abuſe her farre more,<note n="*" place="margin">Leo <hi>10.</hi> ep. ad Bemb. <hi>17.</hi>
                     </note> one calling her a <hi>Goddeſſe,</hi> ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther<note n="*" place="margin">Roſar. Mar.</note> the <hi>Goddeſſe of the ſea,</hi> which is the title of <hi>Venus.</hi> Making of <hi>Mary</hi> the <hi>euer Virgin</hi> a meere<note n="*" place="margin">in Petr. Arbit.</note> 
                     <hi>Quartilla,</hi> that could <hi>neuer</hi> remember ſhe was a Virgin. In euery deed you all abuſe her. For<note n="*" place="margin">Polan: ſynt. l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>24.</hi>
                     </note> as one wel obſerues, when you ſay your <hi>Aue Maries,</hi> you <hi>pray</hi> for her. But wee hold, as to <hi>pray for</hi> her to be moſt<note n="*" place="margin">Aug. ſerm. <hi>17.</hi> de verb. Ap.</note> iniurious, ſo to pray <hi>to</hi> her to be moſt<note n="*" place="margin">Epiph. l. <hi>3.</hi> aduerſ. haereſ.</note> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull and ſuperſtitious.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pap.</speaker>
                  <p>Alſo you neuer vſe to pray for the <hi>dead,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:2171:70"/> the Auncients did ſo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                  <p>Wee dare not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed For if they bee in <hi>Heauen,</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">P. Lomb. <hi>4</hi> ſent. distinct. <hi>45.</hi>
                     </note> we ſhall wrong them, if in <hi>Hell,</hi> we cannot helpe them; and <hi>Purgatory,</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Roffenſ. contra art. Luther. art. <hi>18.</hi>
                     </note> your owne men confeſſe, was <hi>neuer heard of amongst the Auncients.</hi> Now for thoſe prayers for the dead in the old <hi>Liturgies,</hi> they were conceiued (if you marke them) for men <hi>dying,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Caeſſand. prec. eccleſ.</note> and paſſing, not <hi>dead</hi> already, and ſo they are ſtill vſed in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and moſt diligently, &amp; deuour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the Collegiate Church of <hi>Westminſter.</hi> But to
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:2171:71"/> ſtretch, and extend theſe<note n="*" place="margin">Vide epiſt. Vra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſlau. apud Scultet. Annal. dec. <hi>1.</hi> pa. <hi>152.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Collects</hi> to men <hi>ſtone-dead,</hi> and paſt their particular <hi>iudgements</hi> was a pretty pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect of the <hi>Monkes</hi> and <hi>Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ars,</hi> and they were very wel payd for their wit, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uention, as you ſhall finde, when you ſhall haue occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to purchaſe a <hi>Maſse</hi> for any of your kindred <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pap.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay ſay you nothing of the <hi>Maſſe,</hi> for out of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, and derogation from the <hi>Sacrifice</hi> therin offered, you haue bred in the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſuch a <hi>ſleight</hi> opinion of the <hi>Bleſsed Sacrament,</hi> as they make of it, but a bare
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:2171:71"/> 
                     <hi>ſigne,</hi> or a <hi>token,</hi> or a <hi>figure,</hi> or I cannot tell what: And dare not conceiue Chriſt to be there, for feare of impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment, or the high Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                  <p>Wee doe indeed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge no <hi>oblation</hi> in the bleſſed <hi>Sacrament,</hi> but a<note n="*" place="margin">See common praier booke.</note> liuely <hi>commemoration</hi> of that oblation of Chriſt, which he offered vpon the Croſſe for our redemption. Nor any <hi>Sacrifice</hi> at all, but that Sacrifice of <hi>Collects, prayers,</hi> and <hi>thankeſgiuing,</hi> which the Church powres out vnto God at the recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of the <hi>Sacrament.</hi> And theſe <hi>commemorations,</hi> and
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:2171:72"/> 
                     <hi>collects,</hi> are the reaſon, why the Supper of the Lord, was termed by the Auncients, <hi>a Sacrifice, an Oblation, the Euchariſt, the Hoaſt,</hi> &amp;c. But the reuerence due to this great <hi>Sacrament</hi> is as ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruable, as the maner of Chriſts <hi>preſence</hi> therein is vnexpreſſable. The names of a <hi>figure,</hi> a <hi>ſigne,</hi> a <hi>type,</hi> and the like, wee keepe to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound the words onely, but not as though they were keyes to open, and vnfolde the maner of the myſterie. The ſpeech is to be expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded figuratiuely, becauſe<note n="*" place="margin">Schoolemen in 4. ſent.</note> 
                     <hi>This,</hi> and <hi>Chriſts body</hi> (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the pronuntiation of
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:2171:72"/> the laſt ſyllable of the wordes) are <hi>disparats</hi> and of a contrary nature. But Chriſt is <hi>preſent</hi> there, for the matter<note n="a" place="margin">Aug. confeſſ. a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud Caſsand. conſult. art. <hi>10.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>ſubſtantially,</hi>
                     <note n="b" place="margin">
                        <hi>Caluin. in</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.21.</note> 
                     <hi>truely,</hi>
                     <note n="c" place="margin">Melan. in ep. ad Palat. &amp; Granguellam.</note> 
                     <hi>really,</hi> nay <hi>moſt truely,</hi>
                     <note n="d" place="margin">Fortunatus Caluiniſta a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud Greg. de Valent. l. <hi>1.</hi> de praeſen. Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti in Euchar. c. <hi>7.</hi> diſt. Iſtius.</note> and <hi>moſt really, and more truely, and more really, then the bread and the wine,</hi> but for the maner ineffa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, and <hi>vnexpreſſably.</hi> And this is that <hi>Caluiniſticall</hi> do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, you ſo much cauill at, and deride.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 Wee honour the Saints with <hi>Eccleſiaſticall</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation, but not with a <hi>Spirituall</hi> adoration.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 The ancient Fathers made <hi>Orations,</hi> but no <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> vnto them.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb n="142" facs="tcp:2171:73"/>3 The bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Virgin is more abuſed by <hi>Papiſts</hi> who make her
<list>
                        <item>To giue ſucke to a Prieſt. <hi>Vincent. Spec. h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ſt. l.</hi> 7. 84.</item>
                        <item>Mend Thomas a Beckets old hoſe. <hi>Cantip. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 29.12.</item>
                        <item>Heale a ſcabd head. <hi>Caeſ. l.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 25.</item>
                        <item>Clippe a Monke. <hi>Id. l.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 51.</item>
                        <item>Kiſſe another. <hi>Id. l.</hi> 7 <hi>c.</hi> 33.</item>
                        <item>Sing to a third. <hi>Id. l.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 22.</item>
                        <item>Lie betweene <hi>man and wife. Vincent. lib.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 8.</item>
                        <item>Supplie a <hi>Nunnes</hi> place that was gone to a <hi>Bawdy</hi> houſe. <hi>Caeſar. lib.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 35.</item>
                        <item>Bring an <hi>Abbeſse</hi> to bed gotten with childe by her <hi>Seruing-man. Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent. Spec. hiſt. lib.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 87.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4 Wee are ready to <hi>bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> but not to <hi>adore</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques.</p>
                  <p n="5">5 We pray for men <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting,</hi> as the Fathers did, not for the <hi>departed</hi> as the Friars did.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <pb n="143" facs="tcp:2171:73" rendition="simple:additions"/>6 Chriſt is <add>in</add> the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>really</hi> for the matter, <hi>ineffably</hi> for the maner.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 5.</hi> Some idle perſonall exceptions.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                  <p>HAue you any other points of our Religion that you ſtumble at?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pap.</speaker>
                  <p>Theſe are the main points of your religion queſtioned. But ſome aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ons more are caſt vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>perſons</hi> of your <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters.</hi> As that they <hi>lie</hi> wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullie,
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:2171:74"/> and againſt their knowledge in points of <hi>Diuinity,</hi> and are thus zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous in the cauſe, out of a deſire onely to preſerue their <hi>great eſtates</hi> in the Church, wheras our <hi>Prieſts</hi> haue no other worldlie comfort, but the <hi>goodneſſe</hi> of their cauſe, and the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of their <hi>conſciences.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                  <p>Let your common diſcretion be your iudge in this caſe, whether wee, that ground our doctrines vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>word</hi> of God, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted by thoſe <hi>ten rules</hi> I formerly ſet downe, or theſe men, that put all to the determination of the <hi>Church</hi>
                     <pb n="145" facs="tcp:2171:74"/> that is, to their own proper <hi>phantaſies,</hi> and the groſſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of an <hi>vnlearned Pope,</hi> are moſt likely to gull the world, with crotchets, and <hi>Chimaeras.</hi> Beſides, you know how full this king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is of men well read, as in all <hi>ſciences,</hi> ſo eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in <hi>Diuinity.</hi> You know (and yet none knowes it ſo well, as they that beſt know him) the profound learning and deepe apprehenſion of the <hi>King</hi> himſelf, as hauing perfectly digeſted, the very <hi>body and bulke</hi> of all ſacred knowledge. And is this a <hi>stage</hi> for ignorance &amp; impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture to play their parts on?
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:2171:75"/> Or doeth this <hi>learned Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch,</hi> the Lord of 3. King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, woed and ſought vnto, by all the Catholike Princes, palliate his religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in hope of a <hi>Biſhoprick?</hi> Theſe are poore and tooth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe aſperſions. Then for our Eccleſiaſticall <hi>estates,</hi> they are ſo <hi>par'de,</hi> and <hi>pol'de</hi> with duties, and impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons (all which had their O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginall from the Court of <hi>Rome</hi>) that the time of the charge of breeding vp a <hi>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister,</hi> would raiſe him a better meanes then he hath in the <hi>Church</hi> in any other trade or trafficque whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer The King is gracious
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:2171:75"/> to his ſeruants of all profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions. But a <hi>Countrey Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster</hi> cannot inne for the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt of a whole yeere, what a <hi>Ieſuite</hi> can get in an hours <hi>confeſsion.</hi> Laſtly, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning theſe profeſſors of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerty the <hi>Prieſts,</hi> and the <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites,</hi> it is too well knowne they want no maintenance. What by traducing our Nation abroad, and ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing our people at home, their bones are full of mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and their eyes ſwell with fatneſſe; and what the <hi>Statute</hi> hath taken from vs, cogging, and <hi>cheating</hi> hath drawen vpon them, I mean the <hi>priuie Tithes,</hi> and <hi>Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolences</hi>
                     <pb n="148" facs="tcp:2171:76"/> of the Kingdome. But to choke this Obiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in one word. That our meanes is no cauſe to keepe vs in this profeſſion, witnes our Brethren in <hi>France</hi> and elſewhere, who <hi>without</hi> the ſame <hi>means,</hi> teach &amp; preach the ſelfe ſame <hi>doctrine.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pap.</speaker>
                  <p>They alſo inform vs that your Miniſters haue neither <hi>learning,</hi> nor <hi>hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                  <p>It is true indeede, they teach their <hi>Nouices,</hi> that the greateſt Doctor in our Church, doth not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the common grounds of <hi>Diuinity,</hi> and muſt of<note n="*" place="margin">Britanno-Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manus pag. <hi>19.</hi>
                     </note> neceſſity bee put
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:2171:76"/> to his <hi>A. B. C.</hi> againe. But common reaſon can inform you, whether this bee true or not. Againe, they are onely the baſe <hi>fugitiues,</hi> and diſcontented <hi>runnagates</hi> of our own nation, that ſpread theſe rumours, who thinke their Countrie-men the groſſeſt fooles in Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, that they dare thus amuſe them, and lead them by the noſe, with ſuch im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſsible aſſertions. And therefore I will giue you a touch heere, how other <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts</hi> haue ingeniouſly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged the <hi>learning,</hi> and <hi>piety of</hi> many <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants.</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Aeneas Sylui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us de orig. Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hem. c. <hi>35.</hi>
                     </note> Pope <hi>Pius</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:2171:77"/> 
                     <hi>Hus</hi> for learning, and purity of life;<note place="margin">Alph. lib. <hi>2.</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſ. haereſ. tit. Ador. haer. <hi>2.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Alphonſus de Castro Oecolampadius</hi> for all kinde of knowledge, and the tongues eſpecially,<note n="*" place="margin">In annot. in Tert. coron. Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litis. In defenſ. conc. Trid. l. <hi>1.</hi> p. <hi>41.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanus</hi> alſo <hi>Conradus Pellican</hi> as a man of a wonderfull ſanctity, and erudition; <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dradius</hi> likewiſe, <hi>Chemnitius</hi> for a man of a ſharpe wit, and great iudgement; <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterus</hi> all the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> for their ciuill behauiour, their almes, their building of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpitals, and forbearing from reuiling, &amp; ſwearing;<note n="*" place="margin">Enchirid. c. <hi>2.</hi> p. <hi>101.</hi> De pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hib. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>13.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Gret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zer</hi> himſelfe, our ordinarie <hi>writers</hi> to bee (for the moſt part) of great learning,<note n="1" place="margin">Recherches de la Fraunce, pag. <hi>910.</hi> &amp; <hi>511.</hi>
                     </note> and iudgement, <hi>Stephen Paſchier</hi>
                     <pb n="151" facs="tcp:2171:77"/> held <hi>Caluin</hi> worthie (ſet his opinions aſide) to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for zeale and learning to the chiefe <hi>Doctors</hi> of the Catholique Church.<note n="2" place="margin">Lib. <hi>11.</hi> epiſt. <hi>11.</hi> Epiſt.</note> 
                     <hi>Eraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> held <hi>Luther</hi> of that inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gritie of life, that his very e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies had nothing to caſt in his diſh;<note n="3" place="margin">Lindan. l. <hi>3.</hi> Strom. cap. <hi>33.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Lindanus</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged <hi>Melancthon</hi> to be adorned with all kind of learning. In a word, your Writers themſelues did ſo applaud the perſons of their <hi>aduerſaries</hi> for learning, and pietie, that<note n="4" place="margin">Index expurg. diſtinct. <hi>2.</hi>
                     </note> Pope <hi>Clement</hi> the 8. was faine to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand all your Controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie-writers to bee <hi>reuiewed;</hi> and theſe graces, and <hi>praiſes</hi>
                     <pb n="152" facs="tcp:2171:78"/> beſtowed on our men, to be blotted out, and <hi>expunged.</hi> And therefore when you next heare a <hi>Ieſuite</hi> in this theme, thinke vpon theſe true <hi>relations,</hi> and withall laugh at him, and pray for him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pap.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir, I haue receiued ſome ſatisfaction, that mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters are not ſo farre out of ſquare in the Church of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> as I haue beene infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. But yet my conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence will not ſerue mee, to come to your congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, becauſe there are (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide theſe triuiall) many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther points of doctrine ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer heard of amongſt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants,
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:2171:78"/> which be in very deed the <hi>Caballas,</hi> and <hi>my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steries</hi> of the Romane-Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Religion. You haue beene very tedious in your anſweres and declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, I pray you therefore beſtow the laſt <hi>Chapter</hi> vpon me, to ſhew the reaſons, why ſo many <hi>Ladies,</hi> and <hi>good Soules</hi> refuſe to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme themſelues to the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                  <p>With all my heart, I will therefore end my ſpeach with the ſumming vp this fifth <hi>Chapter,</hi> and leaue the euent to <hi>God,</hi> and your <hi>Conſcience.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <pb n="154" facs="tcp:2171:79"/>1. The <hi>meanes</hi> of our Churchmen are not ſo <hi>great,</hi> as to make them maintaine a <hi>falſe</hi> religion, but their religion is ſo <hi>true,</hi> as it makes them contented with <hi>any</hi> meanes.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Yet in other countries, where no hope of <hi>prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> appeares, there ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares an equall zeale of our <hi>Religion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. Our <hi>Church-men</hi> are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended for their liues, and learning, by the pens of their prime aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="155" facs="tcp:2171:79"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 6.</hi> Reaſons of refuſall to leaue the Romiſh religion, collected out of printed Authors.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pap.</speaker>
                  <p>I Cannot leaue my Religion.</p>
               </sp>
               <div n="1" type="reason">
                  <head>
                     <hi>I.</hi> Reaſon.</head>
                  <p>Becauſe, We muſt ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply beleeue the Church of Rome, whether it teach true, or falſe. <hi>Stapl. Antidot. in Euang. Luc.</hi> 10.16. <hi>pag.</hi> 528.</p>
                  <p>And if the Pope beleeue there is <hi>no life to come,</hi> wee muſt beleeue it as an Article of our Faith. <hi>Buſgradus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="156" facs="tcp:2171:80"/>
                  <p>And we muſt not heare <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Preachers, though they preach the <hi>Truth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Rhem. vpon tit.</hi> 3.10.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Blaſph.</note>And for your Scripture, we litle weigh it. For the Word of God, if it bee not expounded, as the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> will haue it, is the word of the Diuell. <hi>Hoſius de expreſſo verbo Dei.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="reason">
                  <head>
                     <hi>II.</hi> Reaſon.</head>
                  <p>You rely too much vpon the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> and S. <hi>Paules</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtles in your Religion, whereas,<note place="margin">Blaſph.</note> the <hi>Goſpel</hi> is but a fable of Chriſt, as Pope <hi>Leo</hi> the tenth tels vs. <hi>Apol. of H. Stephen. fol.</hi> 358. <hi>Smeton. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Hamilton. pag.</hi> 104.</p>
                  <pb n="157" facs="tcp:2171:80"/>
                  <p>And the Pope can <hi>diſpenſe</hi> againſt the <hi>New Teſtament. Panormit. extra de diuortiis.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And hee may checke, when hee pleaſes the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles of S. <hi>Paul. Carolus Ruinus Conſil.</hi> 109. <hi>num.</hi> 1. <hi>volum.</hi> 5.</p>
                  <p>And controule any thing auouched by all the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles. <hi>Rota in deciſ.</hi> 1. <hi>num.</hi> 3. <hi>in nouiſs. Anton. Maria in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit. ad deciſ. Rotae nou. de Big. n.</hi> 10.</p>
                  <p>And there is an <hi>eternall</hi> Goſpel, to wit,<note place="margin">Blaſph.</note> that of the <hi>holy Ghoſt,</hi> which puts down Chriſts. <hi>Cirellus a Carmelite ſet it foorth.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="reason">
                  <pb n="158" facs="tcp:2171:81"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>III.</hi> Reaſon.</head>
                  <p>You attribute all your Saluation to <hi>Faith</hi> in Chriſt alone. Whereas, He is the Sauiour of <hi>men</hi> onely, but of no <hi>women. Dial. of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues and Pauper, compl.</hi> 6. <hi>cited by Rogers vpon the Artic. and Postellus in Ieſuits Catech. l.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 10.</p>
                  <p>For women are ſaued by
<list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>S. Clare.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Mother</hi> Iane.</item>
                     </list>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Som. in Morn. de eccl. cap.</hi> 9.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Poſtellus in Ieſuits Catech. lib.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 10.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>Nay to ſpeake properly, S. <hi>Francis</hi> hath redeemed as many, as are ſaued ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thence his dayes. <hi>Conformit. of S. Fran.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="159" facs="tcp:2171:81"/>
                  <p>And the blood of S. <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> a <hi>Becket. Hor. Beat. Virg.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And ſometimes one man, by his Satisfactions, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemes another. <hi>Teſt. Rhem. in Rom.</hi> 8.17.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="reason">
                  <head>
                     <hi>IV.</hi> Reaſon.</head>
                  <p>In your Church there is but one way to remiſsion of ſinnes, which you call <hi>Faith</hi> in Chriſt, but we haue ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. For we put away
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:2171:82"/> Our
<list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Venials,</hi> with a litle holy water, <hi>Teſt. Rhem. in Rom.</hi> 8.17.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Mortals,</hi> by
<list>
                              <item>1. Merits of the B. Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, <hi>Hor. B. Virg.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>2. The blood of <hi>Becket, ib.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>3. <hi>Agnos Dei, or</hi> holy Lambes, <hi>Cerem. l.</hi> 1. <hi>t.</hi> 7.</item>
                              <item>4. Little parcels of the Goſpel, <hi>Breuiar.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>5. Becomming <hi>Franciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans, confor. l.</hi> 1. <hi>fol.</hi> 101.</item>
                              <item>6. A Biſhops pardon for 40. dayes, a Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals for a 100. daies, and the Popes for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer. <hi>Tak. Camaer. apud Eſpenſ. in</hi> 1. <hi>ad Tim.</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="reason">
                  <head>
                     <hi>V.</hi> Reaſon.</head>
                  <p>You ſtand too preciſely vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your <hi>Sacraments,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire a true <hi>Faith</hi> in the partaker. Whereas with vs, To become a <hi>Monke,</hi> or a <hi>Nunne,</hi> is as good as the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of <hi>Baptiſme. Aquin. de ingreſ. relig. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 21.</p>
                  <pb n="161" facs="tcp:2171:82"/>
                  <p>And the very true, and reall <hi>body of Chriſt</hi> may bee deuoured of dogs, hogges, cattes, and rattes. <hi>Alex. Hales, parte</hi> 4. <hi>q.</hi> 45. <hi>Thom. parte</hi> 3. <hi>q.</hi> 8. <hi>art.</hi> 3.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="reason">
                  <head>
                     <hi>VI.</hi> Reaſon.</head>
                  <p>Then for your Miniſters, euery one is allowed to haue his <hi>wife,</hi> or elſe enforced to liue <hi>chaſtly,</hi> whereas with vs, the Pope himſelfe can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not diſpenſe with a Prieſt to <hi>marrie,</hi> no more then he can priuiledge him to take a <hi>purſe. Turianus found fault withall by Caſsand. Conſult. art.</hi> 23.</p>
                  <p>But whordome is allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:2171:83"/> all the yeere long. <hi>See Sparkes diſcouery, pag.</hi> 13. <hi>&amp; conſtitut. Othon. de concubit. cleric. remouend.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Abhominable.</note>And another ſinne for <hi>Iune, Iuly, Auguſt.</hi> which you muſt not know of. <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed for this time by Sixtus Quartus to all the family of the Cardinall of S. Lucie, veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel. Grouingenſ. tract. de indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent. citat. a Iacob. Laurent. Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit. lib. pag.</hi> 196. <hi>vide Io. Wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fij lection. memorab. centen.</hi> 15 <hi>p.</hi> 836.</p>
                  <p>For indeed the <hi>wickednes</hi> of the Church-men is a prime argument of the worthineſſe of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church. <hi>Bellar. l.</hi> 4. <hi>de Rom.
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:2171:83"/> Pont. cap.</hi> 14. <hi>artic.</hi> 28.</p>
                  <p>And the Pope can make that <hi>righteous,</hi> which is <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous. l.</hi> 1. <hi>Decretal. Greg. tit.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 5.</p>
                  <p>And yet can no man ſay vnto him, Sir, why do you ſo? <hi>In extrau tom.</hi> 22. <hi>titul.</hi> 5. <hi>c. ad Apostolatus.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="reason">
                  <head>
                     <hi>VII.</hi> and laſt Reaſon.</head>
                  <p>You in the Church of England haue caſt off the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Blaſph.</note> whereas the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> is a God. <hi>Dist.</hi> 96. <hi>c. Satis eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denter. &amp; Panorm. cap. Quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Abbas.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
